<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pacquet of advices and animadversions, sent from London to the men of Shaftsbury which is of use for all His Majesties subjects in the three kingdoms : occasioned by a seditious pamphlet, intituled, A letter from a person of quality to his friend in the country.</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36611</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15743781</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15743781</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104590</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104590)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1153:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pacquet of advices and animadversions, sent from London to the men of Shaftsbury which is of use for all His Majesties subjects in the three kingdoms : occasioned by a seditious pamphlet, intituled, A letter from a person of quality to his friend in the country.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Marchamont Nedham. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683. --  Letter from a person of quality to his friend in the country.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:104590:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:104590:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A PACQUET OF ADVICES AND ANIMADVERSIONS, Sent from <hi>LONDON</hi> To the Men of <hi>SHAFTSB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY:</hi> Which is of Uſe for all His MAJESTIES Subjects in the Three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by a Seditious Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>A Letter from a Perſon of Quality to His Friend in the Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1676.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104590:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104590:2"/>
            <head>A Pacquet of Advices and Animadverſions ſent from <hi>London</hi> to the Men of <hi>Shaftsbury, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Ye Men of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>both Lords and Gentlemen,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>IS well, that in this Interval of Parliament, we have ſome time for Contemplation, and reſt from Buſineſs, that ſo we might reflect upon what we have done, as well as conſider what we ought next to do; and in cool Blood ponder the Nature, and probable Events of thoſe Counſels that ſome of us ſo fiercely proſecuted in the <hi>Laſt Seſsion,</hi> 1675; together with the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends of ſuch as firſt ſet them on foot, and engaged us to ſerve them: the danger whereof, while we were in the heats of Paſſion and Tranſaction, it was hardly poſſible for us to apprehend.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>(SIRS)</hi> this being our ſeaſon for thinking, pray you think in the firſt place who gave the Occaſion for ſo long an Interval. Why was it that His MAJE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY was conſtrained to put an End to your High Debates? and by ſo long a <hi>Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> but that it was your <hi>Little Friend</hi>'s Great Aim it ſhould be ſo, and that the KING ſhould not be able to do otherwiſe? I mean <hi>Mephiſtophiles,</hi> the <hi>Faery F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end</hi> that haunts <hi>Both Houſes;</hi> of whom I have been told, the Witty Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> likened him to <hi>Will-with-a-Wiſp,</hi> that uſes to lead Men out of the way; then leaves them at laſt in a Ditch and Darkneſs, and nimbly retreats for Self-ſecurity. This (no doubt) the Noble Duke had not only obſerved long ſince, in his ſrequent Jilting with others; but had alſo (if he pleaſe to remember) freſh experience of him, in his late ſhifting of Counſels ere he left <hi>White-Hall:</hi> So that, I ſuppoſe, all Intelligent Perſons will be wary how they imbarque with him any more. For, this is the prime Quality of the Perſon; now let us next ſee, what the Contents of that LETTER are to the <hi>Friend in the Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly, whoever was its Father, it looks like ſomewhat that would fain get out in the World in the Figure of XLI: for, upon ſtrict view it will appear ſo (as I ſhall ſhew you by and by) with every Feature, Limb and Proportion of the <hi>Old Faction:</hi> inſomuch as there can be no Man, that ever felt the ſad Conſequents of that Year, or remembers the <hi>Sea of Blood</hi> that then we ſwam in, and many Years after; with the Plundrings, Free-Quarters, and Deſolations that followed on every ſide, and what in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd we got by the <hi>Faction;</hi> but muſt reckon himſelf bound in Conſcience and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to bid his Friends in the Country and City too, to learn, by conſidering the dark Contrivances paſt, (whoſe dire Effects a little After-time brought to light) how to underſtand the preſent, and prevent a being gull'd in the future: and to take heed how they entertain fly Inſinuations and Diſcontents about matters above them; or give ear to the Voice of the crafty Charmer.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, for his Country-Friend's ſake, and more particularly for your ſakes, I haſten to the unraveling of this LETTER; which I will not call his; though thoſe that have ask'd him do ſay he but ſaintly denies it, and in ſuch phraſes as ſignified plain
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104590:3"/>
enough that he would not for all the World but be thought the Author, or at leaſt the Intelligencer. So pleaſing is the <hi>Itch</hi> of a little Wit in Print, that ſome Men would not loſe it at any rate. But from you, my good Friends of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> I doubt not to find more Wiſdom, than to be <hi>Witticiſed</hi> out of the good old plain way of Honour, <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Publick Intereſt,</hi> and Peace; or to be <hi>Wiſp'd</hi> and <hi>Lanthorn'd</hi> in the dark by a <hi>ſmall Goblin,</hi> into the <hi>Bryers</hi> at beſt; but rather (I fear) into the Pit of Deſtruction.</p>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>The LETTER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT begins with divers Suggeſtions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. That the <hi>Teſt,</hi> which was under debate in the Houſe of Peers the laſt Seſsion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, was a State-Maſter-piece, firſt hatcht among the Great Church-Men.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>RIght 41. in the very Front! Thus began the STATE-MASTER-PIECE of thoſe Days; it is the common Method of preparing for Rebellion; and ſo it hath been in all Ages: For when any one deſigned it, he firſt aſſaulted, not the Prince himſelf, (that would have been too groſs) but began with ſome one principal Part or Perſon of his Government, and ſo proceeded by degrees to alter it. Thus it was in 41: For though the Deſigners well knew the Temper of <hi>England,</hi> that it would not be Govern'd without the <hi>Old State Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> yet they firſt found fault with the Governours the Biſhops; and when they had taken off ſome of the Perſons, then they next deviſed how to diminiſh their Power; and laſtly, took away their whole Order; and ſo one Pillar of the Throne being gone, it was not long ere they tutor'd the People to the overturning of the other, as <hi>uſeleſs</hi> and dangerous; ſo that you know what became of the Throne it ſelf. Nor were they, by the Rules of Ungodly Policy, to be blamed for this: For, when once Men are dipt in an ill beginning, they preſently think they are bound to proſecute; and each Man concludes to himſelf, in the Langaage of <hi>Catiline,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Ills which I have done, cannot be ſafe</l>
                     <l>But by attempting greater.—</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But why the Bill of <hi>Teſt</hi> ſhould be Father'd on the Biſhops more than upon the other Lords of Parliament, I ſee not, ſince the major part of their Lordſhips were Zealous in the opinion and promotion of it, as a thing that would prove a notable means of the Crowns Stability, and the KING's Peace and Safety. But it ſeem'd more adviſable to your <hi>Prime Engineer,</hi> after he had labour'd to render the <hi>Teſt</hi> as odious as he could, then to faſten it on the Biſhops, that it might the better ſuit with that lucky Pattern of 41. But more of this <hi>Teſt</hi> hereafter, where I particularly conſider it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>2. THat the Biſhops do deſign to make a distinct Party of the High-Epiſcopal-man, and the old Cavalier, by tempting them with the hopes of enjoying all the Power, Great Offices, and Advantages, by overthrowing the Act of Oblivion, if they can get any to fight the Old Quarrel over again.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>LOok ye into that Book called, <hi>An exact Collection of all Remonſtrances, Declarations, Votes, Orders, Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. which was Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1642. and in the Fourth Page of that <hi>Remonſtrance of the State of the Kingdom,</hi> which your Maſters preſented the year before to His Majeſties Father, you'l find the Old Copy of your New Calumny a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops; for, they were then charged with <hi>a Deſign to introduce a Change;</hi> and,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104590:3"/>
                     <hi>by imbroill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g the King and his People with Disputes about Prerogative and Liberty, to create unto themſelves a diſtinct Party, under a Pretence of being for the King; that ſo having the advantage of ſiding with Him, and under the Notion of Men addicted to His Service, they might, in the end, gain to themſelves and their Partakers, the Places of greateſt Truſt, Power, and Advantage in the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who would have imagin'd, that Men could be thus Ungrateful to His Majeſty, after ſo Gracious an <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t of Oblivion,</hi> as to be found reviving the Old Names of Diſtinction? What is this, but to ſet the <hi>Old Quarrel</hi> on foot again? and to begin it upon the ſame Point, of charging the Biſhops as the Cauſers of it? Thus <hi>Nero</hi> made it his buſineſs to ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, and then charged the Fact upon the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Who are they that are moſt likely to be Projecting unto themſelves the Power and Great Offices of the Kingdom, but you your ſelves, who are <hi>ready</hi> to make room with an Out-cry againſt the <hi>Great Officers?</hi> There is one among you, who knows how to drive a Bargain for Great Offices at the price of your heads, if any Body thought it worth the while to truck with him; and then we ſhould know who they are that take Courſes to overthrow the <hi>Act of Oblivion;</hi> and in the mean while do ſhoot Slanders at his Majeſty, and His Miniſters, <hi>through the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſides,</hi> as if it were they that joyntly deſign againſt it; whereas His Majeſty hath been ſo far from breaking the <hi>Firſt,</hi> that 'tis not long ſince he granted a <hi>Second Act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion:</hi> and your Friend <hi>MEPHISTOPHILES</hi> Himſelf had ſo great a ſhare in the benefit of it, that one would even ſwear it was granted for His ſake, or that He principally for His own ſake procured it. Therefore he had beſt take heed He do not bring on a <hi>Popular State</hi> too faſt, unleſs they will beforehand ſeal him another <hi>Oblivion,</hi> leſt <hi>My Lords</hi> the People come, at length, to knock at his Door for a better Account, and ſet up <hi>Brook-houſe</hi> anew for him hereafter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>3. <hi>NExt,</hi> That the Biſhops deſign to have the Government of the Church ſworn to as unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable; and ſo, tacitly owned, to be of Divine Right: toward the attaining of which ſtation, Churchmen eaſily break through all Obligations whatſoever,</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>THus the Blows light on the Biſhops; but his Aim is at His Majeſties Government<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> onely 'tis not time of day yet to let us know what he would be at. For in the mean time he writes fair after his 41 Copy; for, you may read in the <hi>Grand Remonſtrance</hi> of the Commons, <hi>Anno</hi> 1641. that it was charged on the Biſhops in thoſe days, <hi>That they impoſed a New Oath for maintenance of their own Power.</hi> God forbid that that <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance,</hi> which then took the Frame of Government all in pieces, ſhould be thought to be the Act of an Houſe of Commons. Many thouſands are yet living, who know it was but a Party in that Houſe, who, by the help of Tumults continually flowing out of the City, like a mighty Inundation upon <hi>Whitehall</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> did, by Threats and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon both Houſes, animate a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Party in that Houſe, to be able to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe the reſt, and carry on that <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> by head and ſhoulders; as they did alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward many other ſtrange <hi>Petitions, Declarations, Votes,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances;</hi> to the diſhonour of the King, in order to the undermining of His Authority, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Government of the Kingdom: And this way they carried matters ſo long, and with ſuch heat and fury, that in tract of time, the beſt part of the Houſe of Commons, perceiving they were not able to ſtop this Career by any prudent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels or Endeavours, reſolved to ſit no longer with ſuch Company, to be made a State and Property to ſuch Unparliamentary Proceedings; and ſo at length departed from them to <hi>Oxford,</hi> whither His Majeſty and moſt of the Houſe of Lords alſo had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104590:4"/>
been forced to retire from the inſolent Aſſaults daily made by the City Multitudes, which were under the Countenance, and at the Command of that All-commanding Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Commons, ſeconded by ſome few of the Lords; who helpt to hold up the Form and Shadow of a Parliament ſo long, till the very Name of a Houſe of Peers was at laſt Obliterated. A ſad Inſtance it is, to teach their Succeſſors what they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in future, whenſoever ſeduced through Diſcontent or Envy, to affect <hi>Popularity,</hi> they ſhall again (which God forbid) ſeparate their own perſonal Intereſts, and that of their <hi>Peerage,</hi> from the Intereſts of the Crown, upon any (though the moſt ſpecious) pretences whatſoever,</p>
                  <p>Here what the King himſelf ſaid of thoſe Tumults, in His <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs He could beſt tell, who felt the effects of them: and, What perſon is there that ever loved Him, or engaged for Him, would be willin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to ſee His Son, our moſt Gracious King, aſſaulted with the like? Or that can with patience hear, that ſome Lords, and other perſons, are turn'd Tradeſmen and Exchange men in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> City; and become free there of the Company of <hi>Demagogues? [They were</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not like a Storm at Sea (which yet wants not its terror) but like an Earthquake, ſhaking the very foundations of all; than which nothing in the World hath more of horror. No Declaration from the</hi> Biſhops, <hi>who were firſt inſolenced and aſſaulted; nor yet from other Lords and Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of Honour, nor yet from my ſelf could take place, for the due repreſſion of thoſe Tumults; and for the ſecuring, not onely our freedom in Parliament, but our very perſons in the Streets. When I found things thus, I hoped, by my withdrawing, to give time for the ebbing of their tumultuous fury.]</hi> Note here (ye <hi>Shafsburians)</hi> firſt the Biſhops aſſaulted, then the Members of Parliament, and then the King Himſelf: this was the fruit then; and, this would be again the iſſue of your <hi>Little Leaders</hi> trading with ill-humours in the City againſt Biſhops; but that there is a Sound and Loyal Magiſtracy to balance Male-contents, and obſerve both him and them in all their Motions; ſo that it will be a hard matter for that ſmall <hi>Boutefeu,</hi> to Blow up the Government again, by <hi>undermining it on the Biſhops ſide:</hi> for, one Trick of State is not to be ſhewn twice within the memory of man; ſo that now (I ſuppoſe) he hath lived to ſee the utmoſt of his old Trade of Jugling, having Jugled himſelf out of all at Court; and being paſt hope of Jugling himſelf in again (all his Fears being well underſtood, there—) he ſets up at t'other end o'th' Town, to Jugle up a Mutiny in the City; in hope to find Combuſtible matter there to ſet Fire to in the Countrey; and, at length, inflame a Party for his purpoſe in this Parliament, or rather in a <hi>New One,</hi> which he ſuppoſes will be the likelieſt Expedient: And truly, he did as good as tell us ſo in that <hi>Letter</hi> written above a Twelve moneth ſince out of the Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rey to the Earl of <hi>Carliſle</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> or rather impoſed upon him: Which was indeed ſuperſcribed to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but intended for a Fireball among the Citizens here; as appeared by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Spreading Copies of it in all the Coffee-houſes; and the effect which it, and his other Practiſes ſince had; and which lately inſpired Mr. <hi>Jenks</hi> with the wiſdom of a Stateſman, to inſtruct His Majeſty, and move the matter at <hi>Guildhall</hi> in Common-Council, to be managed in the old Presbyterian way of Petitioning; a ſort of Saucy Humility, much uſed by that Tribe in the beginning of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Theſe things ſhould not be remember'd, but that they themſelves are pleaſed to revive them, and give us cauſe to judge, that they hope one day to have a Pull for it in a New Parliament with the Biſhops, and then with His Majeſty. In order to which, <hi>MEPHISTOPHILES</hi> hath one Expedient more upon the Anvile; and that is, to uſe all manner of Tricks that may be, by LONG SPEECHES, and LONG DEBATES among the Lords, and the STARTING of CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TROVERSIES about Priviledge, betwixt their Lordſhips and the Commons, to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104590:4"/>
FRUSTRATE Diſpatches of the King and Kingdome's Buſineſs; and ſo Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate the Preſent Parliament to become Unſerviceable, that he may obtain a Plauſible Pretence, to draw in the People to cry out for a <hi>New One,</hi> as the onely Cure of all our Maladies. But how improbable a thing that is (if not impoſſible) you ſhall find evidently proved before the end of theſe <hi>Animadverſions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>4. AS the Biſhops deſign to have the Government of the Church ſworn to, as unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable: ſo in requital to the Crown, they declare the Government abſolute and arbitrary; and allow Monarchy as well as Epiſcopacy to be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and not to be bounded by Humane Laws.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>MOre Sacks to the Mill upon the Biſhops. Load them till ye ſink 'em: That (it ſeems) muſt be firſt done; then down with Monarchy: that follows of courſe, as we well and wofully remember. 'Tis done then like a Workman, to tell the World, that Epiſcopacy is alterable, that the People may not, in any ſence, own it to be of Divine Right; and ſo it will be eaſily concluded, that Monarchy alſo is alterable; becauſe his Believers cannot believe it to be <hi>Jure Divino.</hi> 'Tis a great Crime indeed (Sirs) in the Biſhops, that they ſtand thus in the way of this <hi>Alterability,</hi> and that they maintain Kings to have any Divinity about 'em. We have had of late many fine Points publickly Printed, and expoſed to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates of the Multitude; ſuch as this, <hi>Whether Kings be made of Clouts, or no?</hi> but, What deſerves the Man that <hi>ſtarts ſuch Hares</hi> as theſe, which no man can run down, but he muſt run the ready Road to Rebellion, and Alteration of Government? which its impoſſible to prevent, unleſs we hold up the Veneration that is due to the Head and Members of this Monarchy. But, had I any thoughts of Rebelling; or were I a Caſhier'd or Broken Stateſman, not likely in <hi>fair weather</hi> to lift aſide my <hi>Rivals,</hi> and get in again with the Monarch my Maſter, I would (had I ſo little in me of a Chriſtian, or a good Subject) take all the courſe I could to gather Clouds about him, and create a Storm; that I might force him to come to me for ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or take me to himſelf again to help him to weather it. Had I long'd, and long done any thing, for the place of <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> and unluckily miſt the <hi>Bag;</hi> and, by all the good Qualities of <hi>Judas,</hi> pretended as high merit to it as any man; or to the <hi>Seale;</hi> or to any Grand Office of State, that ſuch a <hi>Gnat of Ambition</hi> as I durſt venture to ſwallow; had I been bobb'd out of All, I would even fall to Courting the People after the ſame manner, and Preach up the Mortality of Kings, till I and my Myrmidons could fright him out of his Divinity, and replace me, and ſcare him our of the remembrance alſo of all my Jugglery, into a <hi>new Oblivion</hi> to ſecure me: Then would I remove and laugh at all my Oppoſites, and the Citizens too, and leave them at laſt to contemplate my wiſdom, and their own folly. All this <hi>(Sirs)</hi> with the help of one of your <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> Conſciences I could eaſily do.</p>
                  <p>And if this could not be done, then would I march on further, and follow the dictates of Nature for Self-preſervation; and ſticking cloſe to the Multitude, drive them on to do any thing that might hamper the King, and ſhackle the Monarchy; or (if need require) transform it into the hands of <hi>Conſervators;</hi> or elſe (in caſe that cannot be) precipitate my ſelf and it to the very bottom of <hi>Democracy,</hi> rather
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104590:5"/>
than not be revenged on my Sovereign Maſter, for favouring and preferring my fellow-ſervants and competitors before me: The <hi>Poet</hi> ſaith,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>We are Princes all, if we prevail;</l>
                     <l>And gallant Villains, if we fail.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Would not any Man then think it well done of the Biſhops, to plead for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of <hi>Kingly</hi> Government, and of the <hi>Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>opal,</hi> (which is a part of the Kingly) when there are ſome in the World that deſign to handle them without all Humanity? and would (had they opportunity) by a commonruine both of King and Biſhops, too late convince this Nation, that by all means there ought to be a joint Intereſt of mutual preſervation maintained betwixt them; and that the <hi>Monarchy cannot, in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be ſuppoſed maintainable without it.</hi> If this be ſo, (as I ſhall ſufficiently manifeſt anon, when I come to conſider the late clamour againſt the TEST) then 'tis high time for all Men that have ſworn Allegiance, to apprehend that the Government of Church and State ought to be ſworn to, as ſo Divine, as not to be alterable, till they can tell us a way how to lay aſide the Right of Epiſcopacy at this time in <hi>England,</hi> without ruining the Monarchy.</p>
                  <p>If ſo be then I have a purpoſe to make good my Allegiance to the King, how can I ſcruple to ſwear not to alter the Church, which is a principal part of his Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? By the one Oath I have ſworn to him in both his Capacities, <hi>Perſonal</hi> and <hi>Politick,</hi> (which are never to be ſeparated) why then ſhould I deny an Oath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging me not to alter the Kingly Polity of the Church? which is as much the Kings Government, though ſtiled <hi>Eccleſitſtical,</hi> as the other part is which we term <hi>Purely Civil.</hi> Conſider then (ye Men of <hi>Shaftsbury)</hi> the Obligation to both parts of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is equal, by vertue of your Oath of Allegiance; and if his Majeſty and the Biſhops, and many Noble Peers, have thought of paſſing a <hi>New Oath,</hi> they did no more but what is very neceſſary, in the midſt of all the preſent Underminings of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy on its Epiſcopal quarter: that is, they thought it wiſdom to fortifie that part, with Mens ſwearing to it, expreſly and plainly by a new Oath; which is no more than what was implicitely contained before in their old <hi>Oath of Allegiance:</hi> and which is not to be found fault with more than the old, by any but ſuch perſons as either hold it not lawful, or have no mind to ſwear Allegiance at all; or elſe are very fairly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to forfeit it. And yet what a world of fine Speeches, what a ſtir, and what a pother, doth our Author tell his Friend in the Countrey, this, and that, and t'other Lord, made in the Houſe of Peers againſt the Swearing!</p>
                  <p>And every jot as wiſe a buſineſs 'tis (which indeed, conſidering the drift of it, deſerves a <hi>Capital Animadverſion)</hi> that this Gentleman in Print is pleaſed to ſtart ſuch a Queſtion as this, <hi>Whether Monarchy, as well as Epiſcopacy, be</hi> Jure Divino, <hi>and not to be bounded by Human Laws?</hi> What the drift is of raiſing ſuch <hi>Quaeres</hi> among the Populacy, at ſuch a time as this, let ſober Men conſider. A man might eaſily gheſs, what a Monarch, not bounded by a <hi>Human Spirit,</hi> would do to ſuch a Spright as this, who ought rather<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to be anſwered with that old Motto, <hi>Ratio ultima Regum;</hi> which would be hung about his Neck, by a Prince of as little Humanity as this Man himſelf appears to be, after all the Graces and Bounties by him received, and thus ungratefully requited. The Kings one ſingle Act of ſparing ſuch a <hi>Factioniſt,</hi> as well as all the other Acts of his Majeſties Government, doth manifeſt, that he himſelf affects only a <hi>Temperate Monarchy,</hi> to govern by Law: Nor can the Biſhops he juſtly charged with affecting any other, or ever to have had any other deſign about it than this, to teach the people there is ſo much of a Divinity in the Rights and Perſons of Kings, that they ought in their High Station to be Reverenced and Obeyed by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104590:5"/>
Subject, for conſcience ſake. This <hi>Divine Right</hi> is certainly due to them, and to Biſhops alſo who are Governours under them, not to be thought alterable, under any pretence whatſoever, till his Majeſty can be fairly convinced of ſome better way of ordering the Affairs of a National Church, which may more effectually anſwer the Good Ends of Regal Government: and truly, till that be done by this <hi>Letter-man,</hi> 'tis downright Sedition, with Treaſon (I fear) in its Belly, for him to deſign the making of a Party againſt Biſhops, to hinder the paſſing of any Expedient (be it an Oath, or any other) that might fortifie ſo Fundamental a part of the Monarchy.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>5. AND to ſecure all this, they reſolve to take away the Power and Opportunity of Parliaments to alter any thing in Church or State; only leave them as an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to raiſe Money, and to paſs ſuch Laws as the Court and Church ſhall have a mind to. The Attempt of any other, how neceſſary ſoever, muſt be no leſs a Crime than Perjury.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Church!</hi> That is to ſay, The King and the Biſhops; for, the Court is nothing without the King. They are well joyned together; for, take away either of theſe, and they both fall together; the Government being ſo ordered in <hi>England,</hi> that they ſtand Props to each other. Therefore, as dull a Politician as I am, if I meant to raiſe Sedition, or commence <hi>Rebel,</hi> I would not ſay a word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King and Monarchy, (that would be too foul at firſt, whatever my Aim were:) but away with Biſhops; and then, of courſe, I ſhall be able to talk of, and with his Majeſty. But yet, in caſe I ſhould ſo plainly diſcover my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to imbroil the Nation, as Some-body hath done, by baiting the Biſhops both in and out of the Houſe of Peers, I confeſs I ſhould hardly believe a King would have the patience to let me go about, and diſcourſe, and write, and print thus, to drive on my deſign among the Subjects in City and Countrey. It would be a wonderful Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his Lenity, and ſuch as might melt me, or the heart of any Man, that is not in Nature a Tygre, or of the ſtrain of the people of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> into a time Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                  <p>Eſpecially, if it be conſidered, that the ſcope of this laſt <hi>Paragraph</hi> is, to ſuggeſt unto the people, as if the King with his Miniſters, and the Biſhops, were plotting a Deſtruction of the Power of Parliament, ſo as it ſhall not be able to alter any thing in Church or State; nor be able to make and alter Laws in future as their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors have done, without incurring the crime of perjury. This is a ſtrange Age, that no Doctrine will take but that of altering, or pulling down an ancient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before we are provided either of Amendments for what we are to alter in the old, or of a new and better Form, to be ſubſtituted in its room when we take it away. But a thing it is, much more ſtrauge, that one ſingle <hi>Sophiſter,</hi> having lately undergone, and deſerved an alteration of his Fortune, ſo as to have been turn'd out of his great Offices, and the Court too, for his Tricks, ſhould gain the Ears and Belief of ſo many Noble Peers; and ſeal up their Eyes too, that they ſhould not ſee his deſign of revenge through all his pretences: which (alas!) had never been thought of, but Biſhops and King and Court too, had continued very good Men; and we ſhould have had neither Speech nor <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of his, as long as he could have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (nor had we ſo long as he did enjoy) a Courtiers ſhare among them. Nor would he ever have vouchſafed the kindneſs of any <hi>Letters to his Friends in the Countrey,</hi> but the <hi>Oath of Teſt</hi> might have paſſed current, as a good Expedient, for preſerving the Government from any unneceſſary alteration: and he would have told you alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104590:6"/>
Tale, had it hapned that any Parliament-Man ſhould have riſen up then, as vile as himſelf, to act the ſame part for an Alteration (or rather Subverſion) of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: and he could readily have maintained the Teſt very neceſſary to be taken by Parliament-Men: to ſecure both King and Parliament from the ruine deſigned. And moreover, he can tell you, that it is no news for Parliament-Men, before they enter the Parliament, to take an Oath to be true to the Government as it is Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed; and yet not to reckon themſelves ſo bound up by the Oath, as to loſe their power and liberty to debate and reſolve upon ſuch Alterations afterward in the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment as ſhall be found needful. What needed then all this Clamour of his? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Teſt would have done no more than the Oath of Allegiance doth, oblige the Parliament to maintain the preſent Eſtabliſhment of Church and State againſt all Alterations, till King and Parliament ſhall judge them needful to be made: As ſhall be made eviden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation, when I come to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ider it in more ample manner. And yet what a Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tter h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e we had abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>!</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>6. AND <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fabrick, a preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhall be taken from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> raiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a real <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>allneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſtanding Army;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in due time the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> will be mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Fools, but as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Slaves as the reſt of the Nation.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>THe Cavalier and Churchman do very well remember, when it was that they were made Slave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and by whom. Was is not preſently after the Biſhops and Church been alter'd? And by what manner of perſons were theſe things done? Even by thoſe very Lords and Commons, who in their great <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of the State of the Kingdom,</hi> Anno 1641. declared, That they conceived <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ir Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eedings to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> by ſuch M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n as did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e People, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y meant to aboli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h the Church-Government; or to abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lve any M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of that Obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e which he owes und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r God to His MAJESTY, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m they conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſs to be intruſted with the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, as well as with the Temporal.</hi> And in their Declaration of the Ninth of <hi>April</hi> 1642. they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>That they intended only a due and ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſſary Reformation of the Government and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie of the Church; And to take away nothing in the one or the other, but what ſhall be evil, and juſtly offenſive.</hi> And yet 'tis not long after, that we find them Voting and throwing down the whole Church-Government; and, at length, that of the State too, notwithſtanding all the Proteſtations by them made to the contrary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and the World. Therefore neither Cavaliers nor Churchmen can, after ſo late and ſad an experience of <hi>Alterability</hi> and Alteration, be ſuch fools, as not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what they have ſeen and felt, by ſuch Alterative humors as are now aſloat again; and what the Iſſue of them would be, if they might have way: eſpecially, ſeeing the ſame <hi>Presbyterian Faction</hi> are brewing afreſh; and ſo viſibly, that we need not ſeek pretences to raiſe jealouſie about their doings; foraſmuch as they are bare-faced and buſie; and our Projecting Dandeprat, whoſe Actions are accountable, at leaſt within the Statute againſt <hi>firing of Houſes,</hi> openly acting the <hi>Kindle-cole</hi> in Parliament, to create a Party there for their purpoſe: and becauſe he cannot yet find a Houſe of Commons for the turn, you have him and his Agents every where about the City, Preaching up a neceſſity of <hi>Calling a New One;</hi> and from <hi>London</hi> his Doctrine is ſpread into the Countreys, with good Counſel to diſpoſe the People to the Old Way of Petitioning; that by a full Crie, the King may be in a manner conſtrained to give them opportunity once more to try their Fortunes by a New Election. This
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104590:6"/>
is more than Jealouſie, as Mr. <hi>Jenks</hi> (if he pleaſe) can tell you; ſo that our Author might have ſpared this <hi>Frump,</hi> which he ſlings at thoſe few Forces which His Majeſty hath been, and is neceſſitated to keep up to ſecure the Government: of which Forces he and his Partiſans are, by their Seditious (if not Treaſonous) Speeches, Letters, and Practiſes, the moſt likely men to cauſe an augmentation<hi>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſo that if ever a neceſſity ariſe that they muſt be augmented, to prevent thoſe mens purpoſes, the Nation may from hence underſtand, whom they are to thank for it, and how to excuſe the hard condition of a Gracious King, who would rather rule by love, and ſets more value upon a Regiment in the univerſal good Wills and Hearts of his Subjects, than in all the Regiments of force and violence in the World. And, how ſmall ſoever this Letter inſinuates His Majeſties Party to be; yet, if ever God, for our manifold ſins, ſhould ſuffer Incendiaries to blow up a new Rebellion, by their tracing the ſame methods, that they uſed who promoted the former; it will ſoon appear by the many thouſands that abhor it, and its Contrivers, that all the reſt of the Nation will become ready Volunteers, either in Purſe or Perſon, to defeat their Enterpriſes and prevent the like miſeries and confuſions, as thoſe were, that the ſame Faction brought upon us heretofore. In the mean time 'tis but reaſon they ſhould declaim againſt <hi>ſtanding Forces,</hi> becauſe theſe few do ſtand in their way, though they are no great number; and are as a Bridle in their mouthes; ſo that 'twill be a hard matter for them to get out the <hi>Old Tools</hi> to go to Work with, I mean <hi>Tumults out of the City;</hi> which were eaſily form'd in thoſe days, when they had none to deal with but a <hi>naked King,</hi> and a Guard of Beef-eaters.</p>
                  <p>But, Why is it, that he cries out, We are like to be <hi>made Slaves?</hi> To perſwade men to the belief of it, he is pleaſed to inſiſt upon four following inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> Four Acts of this Parliament, which are indeed as high and neceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary Acts of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as could be paſſed by Parliament, to preſerve the Monarchy; and fence it againſt the Deſigns of any new Rebellion, that may in future be grounded upon the old humors.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>7. IN order to this, the firſt ſtep was made in the Act, <hi>for Regulating Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> wiſely beginning, that in thoſe leſſer Governments, which they meant after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to introduce upon the Government of the Nation, they might make them ſwear to a <hi>Declaration,</hi> and belief of ſuch Propoſitions, as themſelves afterward, upon debate, were enforced to alter, and could not juſtifie in thoſe words; ſo that many of the Weal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, Worthieſt, and Sobereſt men, are ſtill kept out of the Magiſtracy of thoſe places.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>Upon peruſal of <hi>this Act,</hi> you will find it was high reaſon that moved the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to paſs it, as appears by this preamble, <hi>viz. That the ſucceſsion in governing ſuch Corporations may be moſt probably p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rpetuated in the hands of perſons well-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to His Majeſty, and the eſtabliſhed Government; it being too will known, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all His Majeſties endeavours, and unparallel'd indulgence in pardoning all that is paſt, nevertheleſs ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y evil ſpirits are ſtill working. Wherefore, for prevention of the like miſchief for the time to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me; and for preſervation of the publick peace both in Church and State,</hi> Commiſſioners are appointed to ſee, that all Mayors, Recorders, Aldermen, and other perſons bearing Office of Magiſtracy, Truſt, or Employment, relating to the Government of Cities, Corporations, and Boroughs, do take the <hi>Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy,</hi> and another Oath; <hi>That they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> declare and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>, that it is not lawful, upon any prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce whatſoever, to tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s againſt the King;</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104590:7"/>
                     <hi>and that they do abhor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by his Authority againſt His Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſsionated by Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And at the ſame time alſo, the ſaid Commiſſioners are to ſee that ſuch perſons do ſubſcribe a Declaration; declaring, <hi>That they do hold that there lies no Obligation upon themſelves, or any other Perſon, from the Oath commonly called,</hi> The Solemn League and Covenant; <hi>and that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawful Oath, and impoſed upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Realm, againſt the known Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was an Act of the whole Parliament; and there's no reaſon therefore why our <hi>Letter-Man</hi> ſhould charge it on the Biſhops alone, but that the main Aim is at them firſt; and for what cauſe I have already told you. 'Tis conceived the ready way to go to work, it having been the beaten way to attaque the Government on that ſide: for this, the Party is a forming; the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> hath been tickled in his own way; and the other ſorts of <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> are to be drawn in, if they can be brought to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Revenges of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and be perſwaded they shall have fairer Quarter under them than under <hi>Epiſcopacy:</hi> for this purpoſe ('tis known) our <hi>ſmall Engineer</hi> turned City-Merchant; and having driven a fine Trade in the <hi>Winter</hi> 75. in the <hi>Great Corporation,</hi> he hath the <hi>following Summers</hi> been laying a Train in the leſſer Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in hope to blow up this Parliament with the noiſe of a <hi>new one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Prologue</hi> to the Tragedy muſt be, <hi>Down with the Biſhops;</hi> this is determined to be the onely neceſſary Preliminary. But that (thinks he, and the whole Knot) is not to be brought about while this Parliament ſits: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the onely way is, to be rid of this Parliament as ſoon as may be, and ſhuffle our Pack as well as we can, to get ſure Cards for a <hi>new one,</hi> to play over again the old pranks of their Brethren. This drift of theirs is ſo well underſtood by his Majeſty, and by all Perſons of Diſcretion and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, that although the Succeſſion of Parliaments be a thing moſt commendable, yet no ſober Perſon, that is well-affected to His Majeſty, and the Peace of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, can approve the bringing on a new Parliament by <hi>Seditious Projectors,</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Clamours;</hi> eſpecially at ſuch a time as this, when we have a Parliament in being; a Parliament which hath had the Honour to Re-ſettle the Crown and Kingdom, after it had, by a wonderful Hand of God, been but newly reſcued out of the Ruines of a late Rebellion: A Parliament that hath done perhaps more for the Preſervation of this well-temper'd Monarchy, than many other of the beſt Parliaments put together ever did before: and I may boldly ſay, becauſe it can be proved by Inſtances of Fact, that they have done more towards the containing of Monarchick Power in its juſt Bounds, than any Parliament ever did, that may be counted to have been the moſt popular and publick-hearted: And beſides this, the <hi>Journals</hi> of both Houſes will ſhew, that they have now lying before them, ſo many excellent Reſolves and purpoſes, that their ſitting to diſpatch them, is the onely neceſſary means to put the Nation into the enjoyment of quick Remedies for our future ſafety and proſperity. And whereas it hath faln out, that they have been unable to do any thing to purpoſe, by reaſon of Differences betwixt both Houſes, you are to know (ye Men of <hi>Shaftsbury)</hi> that the Occaſions of that Diſcord about points of Priviledge, and other Matters, were but Artificial Contrivances of ſome <hi>Broken-States-Men,</hi> and other <hi>Male-contents;</hi> made ſuch by their own ill Humours, and Emulations againſt Men, whoſe Abilities, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Merits, have gotten place above them in His Majeſties Favour and Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thoſe are they that would mingle Heaven and Earth, to create a party to keep thoſe Differences on foot; and therefore the Occaſions are by them made much of, and carefully laid up, that they may be readily ſtarted, when time ſerves, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diſpatches of the publick Buſineſs of the King and Kingdom; becauſe the deſign of the Conſederates is thus laid:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104590:7"/>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> By Tricks to reduce this Parliament, as faſt as they can, into a ſtate impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and unſerviceable, thereby to introduce a ſeeming Neceſſity of a ſpeedy calling an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> To make ſure Work, they have ſtricken in with the <hi>Old Workmen,</hi> and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted the <hi>Presbyterian Party,</hi> the onely <hi>Canker that frets in the Bowels of this Nation,</hi> and which gathers all other naughty Humours to its ſelf; in hope to aggrandiſe a Faction, big enough, and loud enough, to uproar a <hi>New Parliament</hi> for their Turn, if it may be: One main Plot is ſo to order it, that this <hi>Parliament,</hi> who apprehend a neceſſity of holding faſt, in a Factions Time, to that part of the Government called <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as the moſt needful Expedient to preſerve the Crown, may never go off with the reputation of ſpeaking Peace and Settlement to the Nation, by perfecting thoſe excellent Intendments and Reſolutions, which to that end, do lie before them. By this you may perceive, why your <hi>Letter-man</hi> ſeeks to deſtroy the Credit of the Biſhops, as well as of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Whatever hath been done, ſtill the Biſhops muſt be in fault, though it be an Act of the whole <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the wiſeſt Act that can be Enacted.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch, without all queſtion, was that Act about <hi>Corporations.</hi> For of what Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the Corporations of <hi>England</hi> were, may be collected from the time of the late <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi>'s ſhort Reign, when thoſe <hi>Notorious Addreſſes</hi> were by them made to him in Lofty Strains of <hi>Recognition, Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> which was but a few Moneths before His Majeſties Wonderful Reſtitution. And therefore, though it was miraculous, it was not to be ſuppoſed ſo great a Miracle, as in an inſtant to transform the Hearts and Spirits of ſuch <hi>Addreſſers,</hi> into a firm and laſting Frame of Fidelity to the King and his Government: what then could the <hi>Parliament</hi> do leſs for the ſecuring of both, than put Corporation-Men under the Teſt of ſuch an <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Declaration,</hi> as might either ſatisfie His Majeſty, that thoſe Perſons were become <hi>New Men;</hi> or elſe might, upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal of that <hi>Teſt,</hi> give the King a Juſt occaſion, for his Own and his Peoples Security and Peace, to purge them out of their places, and put in Perſons Loyal and Faithful. Moreover, 'tis to be noted, that this <hi>Teſt</hi> upon Corporations was by that Act, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue but to the Year 1663; as ſhort a time as could be ſet for the doing ſo great a Work, as to put things in order, to go on upon a right Wheel of Government in thoſe places for the future; after which they were left to proceed in the ordinary ways of Electing their Magiſtrates and Officers as heretofore.</p>
                  <p>This is nothing but what in Prudence and Providence was abſolutely neceſſary. And the uſe of it hereafter may be this to all Corporations; <hi>That</hi> in all occaſions, be it of Electing Magiſtrates, Officers, Parliament-Men, and doing any thing of Concern to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they do carry themſelves in ſuch a manner (it being indeed their true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſo to do) as not to ſuffer Factions, or particular Factions and ill-affected Perſons, to grow up and get ground among them; for the natural Conſequence muſt be, That at length, if ſuch conſiderable Corporated par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>els of the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> ſhall by degrees be corrupted with Men, who by contracting particular Intereſts, ſhall march counter to the Publick Intereſt of Government, and imploy the Intereſts and Credit of their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations againſt it; then, of courſe, <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> are conſtrained, whether they will or no, to provide for a ſecuring the Publick Intereſt by ſome extraordinary courſe: And when they do it, 'tis not their fault that the uſual courſe is broken; but they properly are the Authors, who by their own Extravagancies firſt gave the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and preſſed a neceſſity upon them ſo to do. And truly, in ſuch caſe, the beſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natured <hi>Princes</hi> in the World, if you conſider them as <hi>Publick Perſons,</hi> cannot avoid it, unleſs you will ſuppoſe what is abſur'd to conceive, that they will relinquiſh the ends of Government, and let all run into confuſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104590:8"/>
So much for the Reaſon of the Act about <hi>Regulating Corporations.</hi> Now for the next Act about the <hi>Militia</hi> complained of.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>8. THe next ſtep was in the <hi>Act of the Militia,</hi> which went for moſt of the Chiefeſt Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Gentry, being obliged as Lords Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Swear to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Declaration and Belief, with the addition onely of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> words, <hi>In purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſuch Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry Commiſſions.</hi> This Act is of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; for it Eſtabliſheth a <hi>Standing Army</hi> by a Law, and ſwears us into a <hi>Military Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>HOw the intent of this Act for ordering the <hi>Militia</hi> can be wreſted to the ſence of a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> is a Conſtruction paſt all Underſtanding: but the blame of this alſo is laid upon the Biſhops: It muſt be ſaid to be their Buſineſs, though of all Men none are more remote from the Concern of it. And as little reaſon alſo there is, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Men it Eſtabliſhes a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> or Military Government. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is indeed a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Force: but in whoſe hands? Is it not in the hands of the Nob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ry and Gentry, the perſons of the greateſt Intereſt, and conſequently moſt concerned in the Maintenance of Civil Government and Laws, Liberty and Property? Inſomuch, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Men will cut their own Throats, as betray either: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the hands of Men moſt intereſted by their own Concerns for Univerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> as contrary to the nature of a meer <hi>Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ary Army,</hi> (for, that he means by <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> as Fire is to Water; ſo that the one, in the very Notion, as well as nature of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> preventive, and privative or excluſive of the other. And in the midſt of all the idle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, that we have had theſe late years, about a deſign of a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reater ſtay to ſober Mens Minds than this Conſideration, That as we have a Ring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> deſigns and Intrigues; one that loves his People; wiſe, and confident of his No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ility <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Gentry; ſo he knows he cannot need Forces to maintain his Government, as long as they have the Power by Law to raiſe them for him: nor can there be the leaſt ground for Male-contents to ſow Reports of this kind, unleſs wicked deſigns of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gainſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſhall prompt them to New Commotions; and then indeed they may have reaſon to fear an Army, and cry out againſt it, before it is in being; becauſe they take mutinous courſes to force it on us.</p>
                  <p>But another fault here found in the <hi>Militia-Act,</hi> is, that the <hi>Lords Lieutenants and Deputy-Lieutenants</hi> are obliged by Oath to declare againſt this <hi>Traiteroas Poſition of taking Arms againſt the King; and that Arms may be taken by His Authority againſt His Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſioned by Him,</hi> &amp;c. Doubtleſs, this Proviſion in that Act, is a point grounded upon High Reaſon: For that <hi>Poſition</hi> and the <hi>Cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>t,</hi> were two Vipers that crawled into the World out of the bowels of <hi>Presbytery:</hi> And out of the bowels of thoſe two, crawled all thoſe Monſtrous Treaſons which afterwards were practiſed. As to the firſt of them, not <hi>Maria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a</hi> himſelf, nor all the curious <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Myſtery of <hi>King-killing</hi> among the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> ever invented a more nice and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable diſtinction; ſo to ſplit a hair, in point of Allegience, betwixt the Perſon of a King and His Authority, that the Subjects might be brought to underſtand, how to kill the Man, and not hurt the Authority; or, (which is all one) how to deſtroy a King, and Juſtifie the Fact, by His own Authority. The fine ſpinning of ſuch <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> exceeds all that ever was done by all the fine Spinners in <hi>Logick,</hi> or <hi>Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks;</hi> and 'tis ſo fine a Folly, that it would crack an honeſt man's brains to conſider it, or puzzle a wiſe man how to diſtinguiſh it from groſs Nonſence in Polity. And yet when it ſhall be told to our Poſterity, what a world of People ſuch a phantaſtick Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104590:8"/>
as this, drew in to ſide with a piece of a Parliament againſt the whole; and againſt their King too, under the Notion of being for Him and for His Parliament, I am perſwaded it will to them be almoſt incredible: And therefore, it was high Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for the Parliament, to provide in this Act of Ordering the <hi>Militia;</hi> that the Arms of the Nation might never come into the hands of ſuch <hi>High-Notional Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in time to come; who, when Arms were in their hands heretofore, ſufficiently tutor'd us in the Arts and Effects of <hi>Military Government:</hi> And ye may remember (my good Friends of <hi>Shaftsbury)</hi> this <hi>Letter-Man,</hi> your own Countreyman, had a fair ſhare in that <hi>Military Government,</hi> and knows the ready road to conduct you to a New One; onely (it ſeems) another Parliament is wanting for the purpoſe, to make this King a <hi>Glorious King</hi> too; as, not long ſince it was written to my Lord of <hi>Carliſle:</hi> little (I believe) to his Lordſhips content or approbation.</p>
                  <p>As to that Second Viper the <hi>COVENANT, Lerna Malorum!</hi> From whence ſprang <hi>Hydra,</hi> infeſting the Three Kingdoms, till ſhe returned into the <hi>Lake of Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> there to ſtare in the Faces, or rather Conſciences of its own Authors and Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes? It came on in <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Domini;</hi> but whether in the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>'is name</hi> more properly, time did try. For, this confirm'd all the miſeries that were begun, and became, as it were, the <hi>Broad Seal</hi> of the Decree of God's Judgments upon theſe Nations. That <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> came on indeed with great Solemnity of pious Pretence, of maintaining us in our former Obligations of Allegiance to the King and His Government, and the Security of Religion by Reformation: and by this fair fraud, I am perſwaded it was, that abundance of men, Conſcientious, but unwary, ſwallowed the Hook, and were caught, not dreaming what ought to be conſider'd; for then they might have found under this Fine <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> there was <hi>Death in the Pot;</hi> ſeeing it had been formed, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, onely by F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ow-Subjects, without, and againſt the Will of the King; for which Reaſon it was indirect, and illegal; and ſo great a ſtranger to the Right Reformed <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtant Profeſſion,</hi> that Subjects ſhould preſume, by <hi>Covenanting,</hi> with Fire and Sword, to force on a <hi>Reformation;</hi> that we can find no example for it, but out of the Records of <hi>Presbyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ry:</hi> Nor is there any thing in thoſe of <hi>Popery</hi> to be compared with it, but onely that <hi>Holy League,</hi> which engaged <hi>France</hi> into many years of Blood and Miſery, before it could be extinguiſhed.</p>
                  <p>They might alſo, had they had wiſdom enough and experience, have conſidered what was then in the heart and foreſight of His Majeſties Father, as we find it expreſſed in His Writings; than the inſertion of which in this place, nothing can be more to the purpoſe, or more ſeaſonable; eſpecially in a time, wherein many of the <hi>Old Kindlers</hi> are viſibly blowing this <hi>Old Coal</hi> again, to revive it; and with it, to over-heat the Brains and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men, into a zeal of the ſame Obligation, in ſtead of repentance that ever they took it. But hear what the King ſaid of it; and 'tis enough to forewarn, and adviſe men of any Conſcience, or diſcretion, in the future. <hi>[That</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which makes ſuch Confederations by way of Solemn Leagues and Covena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts, the more to be ſuſpected, is; That they are the common Road, uſed in all Factions Perturbations of State or Church: Where Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of extraordinary zeal and piety are never more ſtudied and elaborate, than when Politicians a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>itate moſt deſperate deſigns againſt all that is ſetled, or ſacred in Religion and Laws; which, by ſuch skrues, are cunningly, yet forcibly wreſted by ſecret ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ps, and leſs ſenſible degrees, from their known Rule and wonted practice, to comply with the humors of thoſe men, who aim to ſubdue all to their own will and power, under the diſguiſes of Holy Combinations.]</hi> Wiſdom and Truth greater than this, or more Divine, never was uttered by any Prince ſince the days of <hi>Solomon:</hi> And it ought to be for ever written in the hearts of Subjects; becauſe we can ſeal to it, upon the ſad experience we had in our late <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> to the utter ruine of all Religious Profeſſion, which men ought to take care by ſincerity and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104590:9"/>
of life, to hold up in the height of Reputation, as the moſt ſacred thing in the World.</p>
                  <p>Otherwiſe, what we may expect of the pretences and diſguiſes of the moſt Sanctimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Combinations, the ſame king tells us in the following words: <hi>[They are Cords and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ythes will hold mens Conſciences no longer, than force a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tends and twiſts them: for every man ſoon grows his own Pope, and eaſily abſolves himſelf of thoſe Ties, which, not the command of Gods Word, or the Laws of the Land, but only the ſubtilty and terror of a Party caſts upon him. Indeed ſuch illegal ways, ſeldom or never intend the engaging of men more to Duties, but only to Parties: therefore 'tis not regarded how they keep their Covenants in point of Piety pretended, provided they adhere firmly to the Party and deſign intended. The Impoſers of ſuch a League will admit of any mens ſences of it, though divers or contrary, with any Salvoes, Cautions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, ſo as they croſs not the chief deſign againſt the Church and their King.]</hi> There are many thouſands yet living, who can witneſs to the truth of it; that they had no ſooner involved the ſeveral <hi>Parliamentary Parties</hi> in the guilt of that <hi>Covenant,</hi> but they all faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeveral Sences and Conſtructions upon it; ſuch as might beſt ſuit with the ſeveral ends and deſigns of their particular <hi>Parties.</hi> They, like <hi>Samſon</hi>'s <hi>Foxes,</hi> had their heads looking divers ways, but were tied together by the Tails; had one common Intereſt, which tied them faſt to each other in Agreement, for the deſtruction of King and Biſhops. They eaſily abſolved one another, and each man himſelf, from the ſeeming obligations of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> to Loyalty and Government, as faſt as their particular occaſions called them off to other Reſolutions. And if we may believe Sir <hi>Henry Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> it was in the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſo worded, that the <hi>Nooſe</hi> might not be too ſtrict and narrow for Conſcience to eſcape out of it, when occaſion ſhould require. For when that Gentleman came to <hi>Tower-hill</hi> to dye, he told us to this purpoſe, that himſelf had been one of the Commiſſioners that went out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and was preſent there in thoſe Councils, then on Foot betwixt both Kingdoms, which contrived that <hi>Covenant.</hi> And when it was objected by ſome, that if the Terms of the <hi>Covenant</hi> ſhould run ſo high, for preſervation of the King and His Family, as they ſeemed to be, the King perhaps might notwithſtanding be utterly hardened againſt it, and fruſtrate all the good intents of it towards himſelf; And in ſuch caſe, it was propounded in Council, what then ſhould be done? At laſt it was concluded, an Addition ſhould be made to it of that ominous Clauſe <hi>[In the preſervation, and defence, of the Religion and Liberties of the Kingdoms].</hi> A <hi>Clauſe</hi> which was made uſe of afterwards, to prove that the Nation might be eſtabliſhed in a Government, <hi>without any regard to the King or His Family.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For manifeſtation of this Truth, there needs no more, but to caſt an eye back upon that fatal <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of the Army, dated at St. <hi>Albans, 20th November</hi> 1648. penned by <hi>Ireton, Cromwel</hi>'s Son-in-law; the main ſcope whereof was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o prove, That they ought to take away the Kings Life, with a pretence and form of Juſtice, and extirpate His Family. And truly, I have the greater cauſe to remember this, having at that time read the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments contained <hi>in ſeveral Prints againſt it,</hi> to manifeſt unto the Authors of ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and all the world, that ſuch a Courſe of proceeding againſt the King of <hi>England,</hi> is Irrational, Monſtrous, and in conſequence pernicious to the three Kingdoms. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the Argumentation of Colonel <hi>Ireton</hi> carried it: And whoſoever pleaſes to conſult the Contents of that <hi>Army Remonſtrance,</hi> ſhall find that the beſt Arguments he had (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Sword) were all fiſhed out of ſeveral <hi>Topicks</hi> contained in the <hi>Covenant;</hi> among which, the main one fetcht from that afore cited <hi>Clauſe,</hi> was like the Sword of <hi>Goliah; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> like it,</hi> to cut aſunder all Obligations both Sacred and Civil; and was improved to this point: That ſeeing theſe Nations were brought to ſuch a paſs (as the <hi>Argumentator</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s pleaſed to ſay) <hi>That the ends of the</hi> Covenant <hi>could not be attained by a Government with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> King and his Family: Therefore, thoſe ends</hi> being the Principal Conſiderations of Mens Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104590:9"/>
ought to be made good by another Government, without any regard of Him or His, who were but of a <hi>Secondary conſideration.</hi> And thus, out of the Belly of that <hi>Trojan-Horſe</hi> the <hi>Covenant,</hi> ſprang that Hobby-horſe of a Republick, with <hi>Cromwell</hi> on the back of it; who himſelf at length, convinced in Judgment about forms of Government, ſaw and confeſſed, by making himſelf the <hi>ſole ſingle perſon</hi> in Authority, that no Reſt is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad by Government in this Nation, but by a <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this (my good Friends of <hi>Shaftsbury)</hi> I ſuppoſe you will not venture to gainſay, but that it was well done of the Parliament, (and Biſhops too, ſince you will have them nam'd in particular) to paſs two ſuch <hi>Acts,</hi> as might keep men out of Magiſtracy in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, and out of Command in the King's <hi>Militia;</hi> whoſe Conſciences can yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and not abhor ſuch a <hi>Covenant;</hi> or ſuch a Treaſonous Maxim in State; <hi>That the King's Authority may be made uſe of, or turn'd againſt his Perſon.</hi> And yet anon, before the end of this Letter, the Author will tell you of very ſtrong Inſtances and Caſes Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body cited in the Houſe of Peers; wherein it was, and may be lawful again ſo to do. Which confirms the King's good fortune, and the Kingdoms too, in being rid of ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Squirrel</hi> out of Power, that can crack the points of <hi>Conſcience, Party,</hi> and <hi>Politicks,</hi> as faſt as Nuts, to ſatisfie his own Ambitious and hungry Inclination.</p>
                  <p>The third Act that he finds fault with is the <hi>Act of Uniformity:</hi> Of this he diſcourſes as followeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>THat the Clergy of <hi>England</hi> are obliged to ſubſcribe and declare, as the Corporations, Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Gentry did ſwear before.</p>
               <p>That the Clergy readily complied with it, being a ſort of Men taught rather to obey than under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; and to uſe that Learning they have, to justifie, not to examine what their Superiours command.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Bartholomew-day</hi> was fatal to our Church and Religion, in throwing out a very great number of Worthy, Learned, Pious and Orthodox Divines.</p>
               <p>That the time ſet for them to ſabſcribe to the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer,</hi> Eſtabliſhed by this Act of <hi>Uniformity,</hi> was ſo ſhort for the Printing and Publiſhing of it, that one Man in Forty could not ſee that Book, which he was to aſſent and conſent unto.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>AS for time to peruſe the <hi>Alterations</hi> and <hi>Additions</hi> then made in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> they had a fair ſpace to conſider, after the Printing and Publication of it, which was till <hi>Bartholomew-day.</hi> For the principal Divines of the <hi>Nonconforming Party</hi> ſat in Commiſſion with the Biſhops; ſo that what Alterations or Additions ſoever were made, it is known they took ſuch care to communicate them abroad, that it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred how all their Party talkt of every Particular in the City, and all over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and had been carefully fixed in reſolution to find fault with every thing, long before the Printing, and never to conform to it. Beſides, the <hi>Reaſons</hi> offer'd for <hi>Alterations</hi> or <hi>Additions,</hi> deſired by thoſe <hi>Leading Men,</hi> were ſo little conſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble, that there were but a very ſmall number agreed on; ſo that a tenth part of the time that paſſed betwixt its Publication and <hi>Bartholomew-day,</hi> might have ſerved them all ſufficiently to conſider of it, had they been then to conſider: but alas! they had been abundantly ſchooled by Letters before, and by Prints too, ſent from their <hi>London-</hi>Tutors, to be perfect in that old Leſſon, againſt all Reaſon or Moderation, <hi>Non perſuadebis etiamſi perſuaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ris.</hi> So that if our <hi>Letter-Man</hi> had pleaſed, he might have ſpared this Objection about want of time; but he had undertaken to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap what faults he could upon the Biſhops, right or wrong. They muſt be accuſed, though it was the Parliament that ſet the time: This ſuits with the reſt of his deſign, as I told you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104590:10"/>
But then, a very great number of good and brave Divines were <hi>throw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> out.</hi> Thus he phraſes it, whereas indeed they threw themſelves out; They were (it may be) a ſort of Divines of Conſcience, but whether miſ-informed and erroneous, it will concern them to ſee, againſt the great Day of Account; or whether any thing of Spiritual Pride, Singula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Intereſt, or Self-reputation with a Party, or ſhame of receding from former miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Zeal, Doctrines, Engagements, and ways of getting a Livelihood; which of theſe Conſiderations might intervene, betwixt the Day of Publication and <hi>Bartholo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>w-day,</hi> God alone knows, and will one Day judge; who is a <hi>God of Order, and not of Confuſion, as in all the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>However, it concerned the Parliament to fear the worſt, knowing what Doctrines thoſe Men had preached many Years before, and what had been their behaviour; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bar the Church-doors againſt the like Humours in time to come, that they might no more climb up into the Publick Pulpits, to perplex Affairs of the Church; or by miſ-leading people with ſhews of Zeal, cauſe new Infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmations in the State: In both which poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of Activity, had not our <hi>Letter-Man</hi> very great occaſion to uſe them at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he would not now have been ſo angry at their being kept out.</p>
                  <p>What thoſe <hi>Worthy, Learned, Pious, and Orthodox Divines</hi> were, or ſtill are, I am tied up by the <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> from telling; which Act ought to be punctually obſerved as ſacred, by wiſe Men and good Chriſtians, that perſons who have formerly erred againſt His Majeſty, either in Matters of State or Church, may not be frighted into new Crimes for ſecurity, or from making open profeſſion of repentance for the old. <hi>Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</hi> ſaith, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> is more joy in Heaven over one Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r that repents, than over ninety and nine that never went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray.</hi> Therefore, it will be more proper to paint out thoſe Divines by probable ſigns of what we are to expect from them in future, than by Animadverting upon their Actions paſt.</p>
                  <p>If any Divine will not <hi>declare his unſeigned Aſſent and Conſent to the Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> which contains the Publick Service and Worſhip of the Church, what reaſon hath the Magiſtrate to allow him a part of the Publick Church-Maintenance, which is by Law an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to that Service? Eſpecially, ſeeing his refuſal of <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> doth implicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifie, that he will do all that ever he can, to inſtruct and perſwade the people againſt it. Which of theſe two then is moſt ſitting? either for the Magiſtrate to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them, or they with the Magiſtrate?</p>
                  <p>Moreover, If any Divine ſhall refuſe to declare and ſwear, that he believes it <hi>unlawful to take Arms agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt the King,</hi> or <hi>by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſsionated by him: And that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es there lies no O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ligation upon him, or any other perſon, from the</hi> Solemn League and Covenant, <hi>to endeavour any Alteration in Church or State, and that it was an unlawful Oath;</hi> what can be ſuppoſed of ſuch a <hi>Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> but that he is capable of Earthly deſigns? And that he may be ready, when oportunity ſerves, to take Arms, and preach up again the old Doctrine of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tting the Kings Authority againſt his Perſon;</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> to boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, to pull the Government of Church and State in pieces? Thoſe two oppoſite Principles do <hi>mutuo ſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llere;</hi> they cannot ſtand together, but the one naturally and abſolutely drives out the other. Is it in reaſon then to be imagined, that any Prince or State, ſhould have leſs wiſdom and fore-ſight than every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Animal, to provide for Self-preſervation, by Laws that may ſecure the Religion and Government Eſtabliſhed, with Church-Livings alſo, in the hands of a Regular Conforming Clergy? Which Laws there was high reaſon ſo to pen, that they might be as a <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt</hi> for diſcovery, and diſabling of Paſtors, retaining Principles inconſiſtent with Monarchy. Let the ſame Men but turn the Tables, and remember what themſelves did heretofore to the <hi>Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>opal Clergy,</hi> for not engaging and conforming to their wild Phantſies, upon every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of Government; and then let them and all Men conſider, with what front any Man of them can condemn this Wiſe and Provident Act, made againſt the poſſibility of a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104590:10"/>
Return of the like Confuſions in this Kingdom hereafter, to purge out ſuch <hi>Worthy, Pious,</hi> but not too <hi>Learned Divines,</hi> I pray you: Men (it ſeems) of a narrower Swallow now, for an Oath, than the Nobility and Gentry; yet at their own time they have been able, and, while they retain ſuch Principles, can be again, when time ſerves, to ſwallow all manner of <hi>Oaths,</hi> and devour <hi>Nobles, Gentlemen</hi> too, <hi>Clergy,</hi> and All. And this our <hi>Letter-Man</hi> knows very well: who, having at this time great need of them in the Pulpit, is (you ſee) very angry they are under hatches. He only wants <hi>ſuch</hi> a Houſe of Commons as he could wiſh; for, he reckons himſelf ſure of his Clergy; they are of another Kidney than the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Clergy: Theſe he is pleaſed to brand as Men of little Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of a pitiful ſort of Learning, which teaches to <hi>Obey and Juſtifie, not to Diſoute the Commands of their Superiours.</hi> Meer <hi>Milk-Sops</hi> they: but his are the <hi>Myrmido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s;</hi> Men of Arguments as ſtrong as Gun-Powder; Profound Men of Letters, who have written, and can write, <hi>RATIO <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>LTIMA REGUM</hi> round the Mouth of a Cannon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe fourth and laſt Act found fault with is, The</hi> Five Miles A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> paſſed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> introduces the Oath in the Terms the Courtiers would have it. This was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrongly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Lord Treaſurer <hi>Southampton,</hi> Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> and others; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the concern of thoſe poor Miniſters that were ſo ſeverely handled, but as it was in it ſelf an unlawful and unjuſtiſiable Oath: however, the Zeal of that time againſt all No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>conformiſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly paſſed the Act.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>THat my Lord <hi>Wharton</hi> and Lord <hi>Aſhley</hi> might oppoſe it, is not impoſſible; but of my Lord <hi>Southampton</hi> 'tis hardly probable; but if he did, it ſerves for ſome excuſe to Lord <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hley;</hi> becauſe his Lordſhips Intereſt, at that early time of day, was nothing in Court without him, and ſo he could loſe nothing there then: For, it was afterwards that he crept up like <hi>Ivy</hi> upon that old Oak of Loyalty <hi>Southampon,</hi> into His Majeſties favour, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a good place; which while his Lordſhip enjoyed, we do not remember that ever he was angry at this <hi>Act:</hi> Nor do we know any reaſon why it might not have been ſtretc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> (at that time) a Mile or two more, without grieving his Lordſhip, or ſtretching his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: ſo that this Story might have been very well omitted, ſo far as concerns my good Lord <hi>Aſhley.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the Miniſters were then ſo ſeverely h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndled, let it be noted, that now is the time his Lordſhip would be thought to have had no hand in it. But whoſe fault was it then? was it not their own? were they not very ſevere towards the King, when they refuſed the <hi>Oath</hi> contained in that Act, which enjoined only theſe particulars? <hi>viz.</hi> to declare,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That it is not lawf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l, upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That they do abhor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſionated by him, in purſuance of ſuch Commiſſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And that they will not, at any time, endeavour any Alteration of Government, either in Church or State.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now let us reaſon together; Is it rational to imagine, that any Governour will not provide for the ſafety and peace of his Government? Are not <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>All<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>giance</hi> correlative? Do they not <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tuo ſe ponere,</hi> can either be underſtood without the other? Is not the Band of Politicks utterly broken by conceiving the contrary? If a Subject will not declare it <hi>Not lawful to take Arms againſt the King,</hi> Is there not a clear Impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> that he may, or perhaps will, when he ſhall have an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? Is it imaginable then, that any King can think himſelf ſecure of ſuch a Man? or that he could permit him to enjoy the Common Liberties of his Government, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104590:11"/>
to give the Common Caution required by Governours for the place of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Or if ſuch perſon have formerly by any Overt Acts declared, or preached to others, that it is lawful to take Arms, can he with any colour of reaſon find fault with the King, when he demands onely gentle Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion of him, by declaring that he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd his Opinion, and will do ſo no more? And in caſe of his refuſal, can he in his Conſcience condemn the Kings making a Law, to prevent him from doing the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? Come, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> let us to the great Rule of Conſcience, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, do ye ſo to them: for, this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> Now pray tell me, you that are Kings of thoſe little Kingdoms called <hi>Families;</hi> If any one of your Children, or Servants, hath taught or ſhall teach the reſt, that it is lawful to diſpute and fight with you (and perhaps they do it) in your Houſes, would you not think it ſtrange, that any Man ſhould blame you, if you, not puniſhing that Child or Servant, ſhould onely demand this gentle Caution of him, that he oblige himſelf never to do the like again? It's much rather to be ſuppoſed, that in ſtead of that, you would turn him out of your little Kingdom, and no Man could find fault with you for it. Now for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, If His Majeſty, a Prince Gracious and Indulgent beyond all example, hath laid aſide the ſevere part; and if you, by your refuſing to give him the Security of a <hi>Promiſſory Oath,</hi> have in effect declared that ye will not lay aſide or quit that unruly Principle of taking Arms againſt him, what could he do leſs, than to take the Viper out of his own and the Churches Boſom, and not nouriſh it any longer? Whereas by the Laws of God and Man, and by that Law of Nature called <hi>Self-preſervation,</hi> he might have taken another kind of Courſe, for the Security and Quiet of Himſelf and His Subjects; and not onely have ſhut theſe Men out of Corporations, but out of the Kingdom. And yet ſo far hath His Majeſty been from this ſeverity, that the <hi>Five Miles A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</hi> it ſelf hath lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht with very little Execution: inſomuch that thoſe Men and their Friends, have, at this time of day, ſmall cauſe to complain of it: but rather much, for a heart-melting into grateful acknowledgments of ſo great Lenity.</p>
                  <p>If another Pen had been ouſied in this Work of Animadverting, it might perhaps have dropt here many notable <hi>Reaſons of State,</hi> juſtifying the Policy and Prudence of that Act, and its Execution; as to name one for an Inſtance, <hi>Viz.</hi> Seeing that, by the Conſtitution of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the Commons Houſe of <hi>Parliament</hi> have an Intereſt in the <hi>Power of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlation,</hi> that no Law can be made, or repealed without them: And, whereas the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of their Members are choſen by Corporations, it muſt needs be of higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to preſerve thoſe Bodies Corporate, as free as may be, from the Infection of <hi>Preachers</hi> of ſuch <hi>Principles,</hi> as are deſtructive of the Kingdoms Conſtitution and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, leſt in a little time the ſwarming <hi>Proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lytes</hi> of <hi>Nonconformity</hi> come to bear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Bell at Elections, and then Trump a Major Vote in the Commons Houſe, to play a New Game again at the <hi>Old Sport.</hi> For (like bold Knaves as they be) they are Cockſure (they ſay) of Lords enough already. And, its ſaid, 'tis one of you, ye Men of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> that took care to <hi>Print</hi> the Names of their Lordſhips, for the honour of the Buſineſs: particularly, the Name of the Good Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> with ſpecial Commendations of Great <hi>Pains,</hi> Long <hi>Speeches,</hi> and Extraordinary <hi>Honeſt Qualities:</hi> which our <hi>Letter-man</hi> hath taken care, in the next <hi>Paragraph,</hi> more largely to ſet forth to the beſt advantage.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>THus our Church became Triumphant divers years, the <hi>Diſſenting Proteſtants</hi> being the onely Enemy, while the <hi>Papiſts</hi> rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in'd undiſturb'd, were thought Loyal by the Court, and by our Great Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hops not dangerous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104590:11"/>
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>REcollect ye the things of time paſt, and you may remember, it was a ſaying as old as <hi>the Reformation</hi> it ſelf; <hi>That the Church of</hi> England <hi>was like Chriſt himſelf, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied betwixt two Thieves, the</hi> Papiſt <hi>and the</hi> Preſbyterian: and, Is it otherwiſe at this day? for, in ſtead of a Triumph after His Majeſties Happy Reſtitution, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or all Her paſt Sufferings, Behold! how both the ſorts of Adver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aries are plying their ſeparate Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts; agreeing onely in this, How to Plot Her Deſtruction; the Natural Conſequent whereof muſt be this: That, after Her ruine, the <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſtands ready to ſubject the Monarch to a <hi>Single Pope:</hi> the other, to ſubvert the Monarchy, by Inthroning here a <hi>Many Headed Papacy.</hi> The one would Rob the KING of Half His Power: the other, of the Whole. Both will allow of a King, ſo He be nothing; that is, as long as He plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them; If not, they have a <hi>Whip and a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll,</hi> to Correct or Depoſe Him: of which our Hiſtories are full. So that if the <hi>CHURCH</hi> be not Maintain'd over them both, to Defeat their Deſigns of Supplanting Her, tell us then, with all your Wiſdom, ye Men of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> What will become of us? and, What the end of theſe things will be?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>THe next Paragraph of this Letter tells us a Romantick Story of a Giant and the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury. The Giant</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>was my Lord</hi> Clifford; <hi>a man of a</hi> daring and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious ſpirit; <hi>but that the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>was</hi> as daring, but more able: <hi>(Some think he did not well to leave out the word</hi> more Ambitious <hi>too.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he was of Principles and Intereſts diametrically oppoſite to <hi>Clifford,</hi> yet preſently cloſed with him in propoſing the <hi>Declaration for Indulgence</hi> to Diſſenters in Religion.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>SInce the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> is named, Oh! What an occaſion is here for a Comment? Thus it goes likewiſe in all other <hi>Romances:</hi> the <hi>ſmall Knight,</hi> or the <hi>Sq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ire,</hi> always appears an abler man than the <hi>Giant,</hi> and is ſure to get the better. And, 'tis but Reaſon it ſhould be ſo, at this time eſpecially; becauſe in the 9th <hi>Page</hi> of the <hi>Printed Letter</hi> are theſe words alſo: <hi>That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>is a man of great Abilities, and knowledge in Affairs; and one, that, in all the variety of Changes of this laſt Age, was never known to be either bought, or frighted out of his Publick Principles.</hi> It may be, the Pen-man of this <hi>Letter</hi> is ſome pleaſant perſon, of little acquaintance with his Lordſhip; or, he Dreamt <hi>all the World to be made of Oatmeal,</hi> or to have been in a Dream theſe Thirty years: And, ſo we may, if we pleaſe, Dream on, That his Lordſhip is no <hi>Changeling.</hi> Would that had been true (quoth the <hi>Presbyterian)</hi> for, once he became ours. But, (ſaid a certain <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter) let me tell you a Story;</hi> and firſt, I ſay he is a Knave that thinks I mean it of his Lordſhip. <hi>Once upon a time (as I remember) the Old King had a</hi> Dorſetſhire-Eel <hi>by the Tail; which then ſlipt into the hands of our Party: And when we thought our ſelves ſure of him, whip, he was gone, and, in a Trice, Commenced a</hi> Brother-Independent: <hi>which was a wiſe part; and no trick of a</hi> Changeling, <hi>to ſhift Principles like Shirts; and quit an unluckie Side, in a fright, at the noiſe of a</hi> New Prevailing Party, <hi>with whom he ſtaid, till he grew up to the ſize of a great</hi> Commonwealths-man, <hi>and made Hay in the Sun-ſhine, until the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth <hi>and</hi> Cromwel <hi>were brought to Bed of a ſtrange new kind of</hi> Monarchy <hi>in the Houſe of</hi> Commons; <hi>a Three or four hundred-headed Monarchy, called,</hi> The Fifth Monarchy; <hi>and in thoſe days it was alſo called,</hi> Cromwels Little Parliament; <hi>in which his little Lordſhip became one of the Princes among a Drove of</hi> Changelings. <hi>But there having spied out</hi> Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel<hi>'s purpoſe of Matching to another ſort of Monarchy of his own, his little Lordſhip then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104590:12"/>
                     <hi>like a conſtant ſteady m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n to his own main Point, to Trepan them, and to ſtrike in with him; and lent him a helping hand towards the confounding of</hi> Fifth-Monarchy, <hi>to make way for a New One under the Name</hi> Protector. <hi>Then, in this Scene of Affairs, be being made a</hi> Protectorian Privy-Counſellour; <hi>and, after a while, be aſpiring alſo to become the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector's <hi>Son-in-Law;</hi> Cromwel <hi>(who well enough underſtood him) either diſdai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing, or not daring to take him ſo near into his boſom, took occaſion alſo to be quit of him out of his Council: So that now it was high time indeed, of neceſſity, to turn back to the OLD HONEST POINT OF THE COMPASS, and get in again, to be thought a New Man of His Majeſties Party. This was no hard matter, to be done by a man of his dapper Conſcience, and dexterity, that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n Dance through a Hoop; or that can be a T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mbler through Parties; or a ſmall Teazer of Religions; and Touzer of Factions; a Pettifogger of Politicks; the very Windmill and Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cock of every</hi> GODLY PARTY: <hi>He, even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, turned again to the Tents of the wicked. For, to go on with my Story (quoth the</hi> Presbyter) <hi>no ſooner had</hi> Cromwell <hi>done his do with him, and ſented him; and, like a true Intrigu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>-Maſter, out-done him, and sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed him out; but being thrown o're-board out of</hi> Two New Monarchies, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e immediately tackt and got aſhore again on the skirts of the King's old Monarchy; that is, he ran in as near it as be could at that time; and, for his own ſake, reſolved to be as true as he could for it, by imbarking in a new Kindred of the Royal Party, ſeeing he could not catch the</hi> Cromwellian. <hi>To make ſhort my Tale,</hi> Sir, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e matcht himſelf then into a Noble Family (one of thoſe that in the late Troubles had beſt deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed of His Majeſty) with a Lady that was Niece to a late Noble Lord; who (as he well knew) had Merit-Royal enough, to anſwer for all the paſt faults of a ſmall wandring Politico, and make him paſs for a Royaliſt, if Royalty came in play again. In the mean time, being out of all Publick Councils, he was at leaſure to make Court to all private Male<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>tents againſt</hi> Oliver; and whereſoever he found a ſore, there he rub'd hardeſt, till the end of the reign of Richard, <hi>and of the</hi> Wallingſordian <hi>Party, for, by this time the</hi> Rump <hi>was got in again; and then he got in again with the</hi> Rump; <hi>not into the Houſe, but into the hearts of ſome of its principal Members and Actors, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eame a buſie man to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y them into the reach of their own deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ry. And now you have him thus far on his way, you may be ſo charitable, if you pleaſe, as to imagine, that all this variety of changes was meant by him, on purpoſe to bring about His Majeſties</hi> Happy Reſtitution. <hi>Indeed one would think ſo, conſidering the Bounties h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> immediately after received from the hand of a moſt gracious King; Honors, Offices, Profits, and Preforments; and theſe, in tract of time, advanced to the utmoſt magnitude, with many private Favours; ſo that if he was never bought out of his publick Principles, yet he was ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> for his private, though never ſatisfied; till at the old game of ſhifting Perſons and Parties alſo at Court, he at le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gth play'd himſelf quite out of Play: and ever ſince, in the Summer-time, you have him a Fox-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ting not f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r from</hi> Shaftsbury; <hi>in Winter, about</hi> London-City, <hi>to ſtrike in with the herd of all Opinions, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unting out old Principles in</hi> this Foreſt of Chimneys. <hi>And becauſe we</hi> Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>byters <hi>are ready to start them, we pray he may have grace to purſue the chace, and never leave us in the lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch any more: And, that our</hi> Brother-Independents <hi>may be brought to forget, how he helpt to train ſome of them to the Gallows. May they leave off bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when he comes into the City; and not do as dogs do at a</hi> Pell-monger, <hi>when he paſſes through a Country-Town: For, even thoſe poor</hi> Animals <hi>are more prudent, than to be at peace with any, whoſe Trade it hath been to hang and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lea them. But let their mouths be ſtopt; and may be never ſerve us, as he ſerved them. And may this Tale of mine never be told again to the reſt of our Brethren: Nor this E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l be roſted as the Rump was in the ſtreets of</hi> London: <hi>For, truly i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ad never been told at all, if I thought any man could be ſo fooliſh and malicious, as to think my good Lord</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>is meant in any part of the Story. But, 'tis brought in here, only to ſhow how curiouſly Contrari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s do illuſtrate each other; and, what</hi> Eels <hi>and</hi> Serpents <hi>ſome men in the World will appear to be, if their qualities and conditions be compared with the Excellencies of that noble Lord;</hi> who was <hi>never</hi> bought, <hi>nor</hi> frighted, <hi>out of his Publick Principles—</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104590:12"/>
Thus far went the <hi>Presbyter</hi> with his Tale; and deſired any man to match it in <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> or <hi>Bocca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi> No wonder then if his Lordſhip went beyond my Lord <hi>Clifford.</hi> And, the Ieſs are we to wonder at all the great things ſaid of my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> in this <hi>LETTER,</hi> if it were true, which was ſaid at ſeveral Coffee-houſes, when it firſt came out in Print; That his Lordſhip was no ſtranger to its compilement; though 'tis written in the ſtile of ſome other perſon.</p>
                  <p>For, in the ſame <hi>Paragraph</hi> we are told, that when the War was to be made with <hi>Holland,</hi> the Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> adviſed the King to quiet all <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in Religion at home, with granting <hi>the Declaration of Indulgence:</hi> and, <hi>that the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>though a man of principles and intereſt oppoſite to the other, preſently cloſed with his Advi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> But, he doth not tell us the Reaſon, why the Earl became hot for <hi>Indulgence:</hi> you are to know, it was then a time of day, that his Lordſhip had worn out his little Intereſt in <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and all affection for it; and ſaw alſo, that many at Court began to be ſick of him; ſo that it was high time, perceiving an uncertainty of his Court-Station, to provide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Retreat into ſome <hi>Popular Faction.</hi> He had long done it before, for fear he might in an ill day have need of them; therefore ever and anon the ſprinklings of his <hi>Court-holy-water</hi> were beſtowed upon many of the <hi>Good People;</hi> and ſome ſmall good Offices he did for them, that the reſt of the Perſecuted might know where to find a Patron: So that with the one hand he ſwept away as many Court-advantages out of the Publick, and was as deep in as any man; with the other hand he upheld a Stock going with the Pious Party.</p>
                  <q>—Lucri bonus odor Ex re qualibet.—</q>
                  <p>God himſelf made the World of <hi>Diſcordia Semina Rerum;</hi> Why then may not men thus build their Fortunes? but he never lov'd <hi>Linſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y-Wolſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> to be worn by his Loyal Subjects; nor ever liked, that men ſhould thus reconcile <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> ſo as to make their Markets of them both together: yet this was the conſtant Trade ſince the <hi>Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution.</hi> Nor is his Lordſhip without Example and Precedent for it; it having been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the old Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and other Courtiers in the days of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> &amp;c. And many times, old faſhions will up again among ingenious Tailors, who alwayes take their meaſures in every employment. There is Goſpel too for this: thus did the <hi>unj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>st St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ward</hi> provide, in caſe he ſhould be turned out of his Stewardſhip. Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then did his Lordſhip, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eather himſelf among the <hi>Men of the World</hi> ſo long before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, that when the time ſhould be over, and the Chancellorſhip be rendred, he might; with a ſure friend, <hi>Mammon,</hi> be any where welcome, and have all deeds forgotten which were done in darkneſs; being next to begin the World again, by ſetting up anew among the <hi>Children of Light,</hi> the Old Trade of crying out <hi>Popery and Prieſts; Biſhops, Evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, and Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>evances;</hi> and, Now alſo, <hi>No Parliament:</hi> but, a <hi>New One</hi> (as like the <hi>Old One</hi> as may be) can do the BUSINESS of his Lordſhip and the Nation. There is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to be thought on but one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that is a very pleaſant one: <hi>Call back my Lord to Court;</hi> then all will do well again, and he will ſave me the labour of te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing the whole <hi>Intrigue</hi> of his Matters. Call back my Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> too, and his Lordſhip ſhall never more quarrel him about <hi>Indulgence, Popery, Parliament,</hi> or any thing elſe: Yea, and he ſhall aſk him pardon too for ſo artificially contriving that fine Fiction or S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, ſuppoſed to have been ſpoken concerning himſelf and Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> when alive; but framed to ſcandalize him after his death; not ſparing reflections even upon His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſty alſo Himſelf, and His affairs; that ſo he might, by uſing the Stile of a Third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, act an eſtentation of his own being the onely Stateſman, that took care of <hi>Indulgen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, Trade, Religion, Kingdom</hi> and All; as you may find at large in the 4th and 5th <hi>pages</hi> of this <hi>LETTER.</hi> But you have been already ſhewn, how long it was before his Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Zeal br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke ſorth with ſo bright a flame, and what the end of it may be; even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104590:13"/>
                     <hi>univerſal Inflammation,</hi> if the New practiſing of the Old Deluſions be not prevented.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe here hath been mention often made of my Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> with intent of diſadvantage to his memory; therefore, ere I diſmiſs this part of the <hi>LETTER,</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be amiſs to ſhew you a better Picture of him, as it was drawn alſo by the lucky hand of the good Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> but it was in a time when his Lordſhip had a Being in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and was willing to Court him that was his Rival in the Treaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, rather than not hold on his new Office of Chancellor. The preciſe time was, when his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip gave the Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> the Oath of Lord Treaſurer in the Exchequer-Chamber, 5 <hi>Decem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1672, where, in his Speech, he began with my Lord <hi>Clifford's Integrity, Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Experience in Affairs;</hi> and that therefore the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad choſen him to be His Lord Treaſurer: <hi>A Place that requires ſuch a man, as our Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Maſter's Wiſdom found fit for it; from whoſe Natural Temper we may expect Courage, Quickneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and Reſolution; from whoſe Education, Wiſdom and Experience; and from whoſe Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, that Noble and Illuſtrious Houſe of the</hi> Cliffords; <hi>an Heroick Mind, a Large Soul, and an unſhaken Fidelity to the Crown.</hi> And when he comes to conclude, he adds to him theſe words: <hi>[I wiſh, or rather proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſie, your exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ding all your Pred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ſſors in this Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; The Abilities and Fidelity of the Renowned Lord</hi> Burleigh; <hi>The Sagacity, Quickneſs, and great Diſpatch of his Son the Lord</hi> Salisbury; <hi>and the Uprightn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſs, Integrity, and Wiſdom, of that great Man that went laſt before you, the Earl of</hi> Southampton.</p>
                  <p>Now, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you that are Friends of Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> if you have any care of his Reputation, adviſe him to deſire the Printer to blot out all the Characters of my Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> in the Second Edition of this LETTER, and put in theſe: or at leaſt, for his <hi>Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hips</hi> ſake, have not ſo hard an opinion of <hi>Clifford:</hi> or elſe be pleaſed to do my Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> and your ſelves <hi>this Right,</hi> as to ſuſpend your opinion of <hi>this Lord,</hi> till you are ſure i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> can be a good one. But if then you find no cauſe to believe all the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries which were at the time of <hi>Clifford's</hi> Fall, hold on ſtill, if you can, the humour of believing all the other Devices of his <hi>little Lordſhip;</hi> till he at length ſerve you, as he hath ſerved all the reſt of his Believers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe next Contents of the</hi> Letter <hi>are theſe:</hi> Viz.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Penner thereof wiſhes,</hi> The Declaration for Indulgence Vight have had a longer continuance, and a better reception; But <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> the Biſhops took offence at it.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>ANy thing to lay load of Envy upon the <hi>Biſhops:</hi> That is a main deſign of the LETTER. At that Corner of the Monarchy, its old Enemies are to make the new On-ſet: and then what follows? The Annals of the late Reign of <hi>Presbytery</hi> will tell you nothing but <hi>Violent Perſecution.</hi> Not a word in thoſe days of <hi>Indulgence;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo much as to the <hi>Brother-Independents;</hi> whoſe true Intereſt it is as much as the <hi>Epiſ o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parians,</hi> to preſerve the preſent Government by Epiſcopacy: For, let the <hi>Presbyter</hi> up with his Throne again, and both the other will be alike expoſed to his mercy. Suppoſe the worſt you can of one Biſhop in a County, yet paſt experience hath told us, we had better have him there than a mean upſtart Inſulter over both, to <hi>play the Devil for Gods ſake,</hi> in every Pariſh. The reſt of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are therefore to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>der, That as the <hi>Epiſcoparian's</hi> greateſt Jealouſie is at the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> becauſe the Aims of them both being at a National Form, they cannot both ſtand together, but the one muſt of neceſſity deprive the other; ſo, foraſmuch as all other <hi>Nonconformers</hi> lay no claim to a <hi>Church-National,</hi> but in Spiritual Matters ſeek only <hi>Toleration</hi> and <hi>Indulgence;</hi> They cannot, if they pleaſe to lay aſide old animoſities, give any <hi>Ombrage</hi> or Jealouſie to the <hi>Epiſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian;</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104590:13"/>
becauſe in their way of Churching, they deſign only a private Rule over one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Their only Concern then is, by a total quitting of all Intrigues, or correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Counſels with that falſe Brother the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> the natural common Enemy of their way of Churching, as well as of the <hi>National:</hi> which being cordially done in ſuture, and all cauſe of Jealouſie, on their parts, being thereby removed from the Governours, there can be no doubt but they may be induced, to allow them a <hi>fair and laſting Indulgence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, it ought to be conſider'd, though the Biſhops be charged by our <hi>Letter-Man</hi> as the Undoers of the <hi>Indulgent D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>laration;</hi> it was not They, but the Parliament that undid it; it being by both Houſes judged inconvenient to be continued, by reaſon it was thought prejudicial to ſome Laws made for an Uniformity in Matters of Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and conſequently an Intrenchment upon Law: ſo that the Parliament was therein led by <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſon of State,</hi> when they beſought His Majeſty for the cancelling of it: the Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> were concerned in it no otherwiſe than the Lords <hi>Temporal;</hi> and it was, upon the Joint-Application of both Lords and Commons, recalled. The Inference then which I would offer at from theſe Diſcourſes, is; That if thoſe aforeſaid Diſſenters would by Overt-Acts of Behaviour in future, make it evident to the Parliament, that they are in heart alienated and departed from the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> the <hi>great common Enemy of the Crown,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Church,</hi> 'tis not impoſſible (yea, perhaps not improbable) but that the ſame Parliament may then come to ſee it <hi>Reaſon of State</hi> alſo, to find out ſome Expedient to make a difference, in execution of Law, betwixt Them and the <hi>Irreconcileable Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> notwithſtanding the ſeverity of Laws at preſent; eſpecially if the Houſes once ſee cauſe given them to apprehend, That ſuch <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are reſolved to become as loyal and ſerviceable to his Majeſty and the Government here, as Diſſenters were heretofore in <hi>France</hi> unto King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth.</p>
                  <p>And truly, ſeeing there is this difference betwixt the <hi>ordinary Diſſenters</hi> and the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters;</hi> that the latter is <hi>e directo</hi> inconſiſtent with all Monarchy, becauſe <hi>Presbytery</hi> claims to be <hi>underivative</hi> from any Secular Monarch, and <hi>in ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ad Spiritualiae,</hi> doth as it were uſurp his Power: and ſeeing the former, while they ſeek only an <hi>Indulgence,</hi> may well enough conſiſt with our <hi>Engliſh Monarchy;</hi> there is no queſtion but they may, in due time, if they behave themſelves wiſely, obtain their deſired Liberty. For, in the very following Lines of the LETTER, our Author ſignifies, <hi>That at the next meeting of the Parliament, the Biſhops promoted the Proteſtant Intereſt ſo high, that an Act came up from the Commons to the Houſe of Lords in favour of the diſſenting Proteſtants, and had paſſed the Lords but for want of time.</hi> What hath been may be: ſo that if the <hi>ordinary Diſſenters</hi> ſhall be ſo wiſe, as to mind their true Intereſt, which really lies in a hearty complaiſance with the Intereſt of the Government, the like may ſoon be done in favour of them again.</p>
                  <p>Next, he tells us, <hi>There was another Act then paſſed the Royal Aſſent, for the excluding all Papiſts from Office; in the oppoſition of which the Lord Treaſurer</hi> Clifford <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ll: and yet to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his ruine, this Seſsion had the ſooner end.</hi> As for the Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> me thinks he might before now have been left at reſt in his Grave: but there is (it ſeems) another Lord in the World is reſolved he ſhall not; becauſe while his Lordſhip tugg'd hard, and lay gaping for the Office of <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> my Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> got between and carried it away; for which he will never forgive his memory, nor any of his Friends. Nothing could pleaſe after this; no not the <hi>Great Seal</hi> it ſelf, though one would have thought that enough to fill the Swallow of any <hi>Gnat.</hi> But Oh! the Dear Bag was gone, the Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t-end of all his hopes, and ſo neither <hi>Seal</hi> nor <hi>Purſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> could ſatisfie! Nothing now but Revenge; for then his Lordſhip ſaw plain the Mortality of his own Court-Intereſt drawing on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which had been long before forfeited by many a Juggle. Then his Piety began to work, when his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs had nothing to work upon; and nothing after this could be thought of, but Fire
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104590:14"/>
and Flames of Zeal, to ſcatter about the Court and Kingdom. A loud and ſudden Cry muſt be raiſed in fear of <hi>Popery,</hi> by pretence of which <hi>(the old trick)</hi> the Nation was to be forthwith intoxicated, and the Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> confounded; and all Papiſts alſo were to be put out of Office, becauſe the Maker of this Out-cry was in fear to be ſo. I write not this to plead for their being in Office; but only to obſerve how pat the little Adverſary timed all things, for his own purpoſe of commencing the new Game of <hi>Popularity.</hi> He foreſaw his own Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and labour'd hard to get in elſewhere, before they had quite thrown him out at <hi>White-Hall;</hi> that ſo when he went off, he might in a new World turn up Trump, as the Faith's great Defender againſt Popery. This was the reaſon why he ſpurr'd on that <hi>Act</hi> ſo eagerly, to run Papiſts out of Office; and why he afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo vigorous in putting the <hi>Act</hi> in execution: for, in all the time ſince the King's <hi>Happy Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>auration,</hi> we never heard, till this ſudden ſit, of his Lordſhips having been in any fright before about the Papiſts, or any other ſort of Religion whatſoever. So that from the time of this firſt fright we are to reckon the Riſe of all the Jealouſies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts that have enſued lately, or which may enſue, about the Affairs of the Government; and of all the late ill Impreſſions, which have been craftily and moſt induſtriouſly made upon the minds of the people, to prepare them (if poſſible) for a Mutiny.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BUt the Letter goes on thus:</hi> In this poſture matters were found in the Seſſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that began <hi>Octob.</hi> 27. 1673. which being ſuddenly broken up, did nothing.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>'Tis a condition of Affairs much to be lamented, that ſo many Seſſions of Parliament have of late been broken <hi>Re infecta;</hi> and we might very much wonder at it, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering His Majeſties great delight which he hath had in the good Advices and Affections of His Parliament, did we not know that ſome <hi>Envious Ones</hi> made it their Buſineſs to <hi>ſow Tares,</hi> and caſt Blocks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the way to impede all happy Proceeding; that either Houſe might be Imbroiled in its ſelf, and both with one another; and ſo be utterly incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated for any diſpatch of Publick Buſineſs. The Inſtances are too ſad to be mentioned, and I wiſh they were for ever in oblivion, which neceſſitated His Majeſty, for the very Honour of Parliament it ſelf, and of His Government, to put an end to many ſtrange De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and Controverſies, which could by no other means be done, but by ending the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Seſſions. For, even in that Houſe, whoſe true Intereſt is inſeparably and more eſpecially annexed to that of the Crown Imperial of this Realm, and cannot ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, there was found a new <hi>Lord,</hi> this laſt <hi>Seſſion,</hi> whoſe Speech (if we may believe a Paper called a Speech, carefully Printed under the Name of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury)</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many ſtrange Paſſages, upon the Debate of appointing a day for the hearing of Dr. <hi>Shirley</hi>'s Cauſe by the <hi>Peers:</hi> which ſhew plainly enough, who it was which backt and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fooled the Doctor to a perpetual attendance on that Buſineſs; not for any good will to him, who (poor Man!) was made a meer Stalking-horſe, but to catch other ends, and create Miſchief to King and Kingdom, by ſtrangling the great Affairs and Hopes of His Majeſty, in the mid'ſt of His many preſſing Publick Occaſions for Supplies; to the want of which Supplies in good time, we are to aſcribe the late loſs of Repute, with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Publick Inconveniences and Damages in our Naval Intereſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which have been complained of. Such Men there are as ſtudy firſt how to tye up the Hands of the King and His Miniſters with Neceſſity, and then make the People cry out at them, for not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they were diſabled to do. And therefore, that the Nation may know to what Male-content the King and People do owe thoſe Damages, and the fruitleſneſs of the laſt Seſſion of Parliament; and from thence g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſs who it was that drave the deſign of fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104590:14"/>
alſo the ſeveral Seſſions that went before it: It will not be amiſs to give the World ſome account here of divers Paſſages of that Speech, Printed with the Title of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury:</hi> which no Man that reads but would ſwear it his.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Speech</hi> confeſſes the Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> and the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> had at the ſame time made Speeches to ſhew, that to ſet a day to enter upon a Hearing in the Lords Houſe, of the Cauſe of Dr. <hi>Shirley,</hi> before the Great Concerns of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in Supplies of Money, and other Bills ſhould be diſpatched, would be to induce ſeveral Grand Inconveniences: As firſt, <hi>That ſeeing both Houſes had been highly engaged in Conteſts with each other about their respective Priviledges, occaſioned by that Cauſe, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of a ſhort day for their Lordſhips to hear it, would immediately bring on the like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts again, and ſo cauſe a Breach betwixt the Houſes:</hi> and, Secondly, <hi>That after ſuch a Breach, made for the ſake of a private Cauſe, no ordinary way being left for dispatch of the many Publick Bills depending in the Houſes, or for raiſing of Moneys; the whole Buſineſs of Naval Preparations, and of other Great Affairs, and of the Reputation and Intereſts of the King and Kingdom, at home and abroad, would unavoidably fall to ruine.</hi> And their Lordſhips were told, <hi>They could not but be convinced in their Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iences, that if that matter of</hi> Shirley <hi>were then proſecuted, it muſt cauſe a Breach.</hi> This was the Sence alſo of moſt other Noble Lords.</p>
                  <p>But alaſs! that <hi>Printed Speech</hi> makes the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ring another Tune, as if his Lordſhip had other Publick Buſineſs, or as if it had no longer been <hi>Shirley</hi>'s private Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, but his Own: ſo that if we may believe that Print, the People need no other Evidence to ſhew who was the Deſigner of the laſt Seſſions of Parliaments non-effect; or to enable them to gheſs who it was that ſpoiled ſeveral foregoing Seſſions, by ſpinning the like long Speeches, to ſtart and cheriſh Controverſies, inſtead of doing Buſineſs. And from thence they may do well to conſider, if the like ſhall be done again, what kind of Man that is, who ſhall endeavour to render a Parliament of no Effect: And what a difference can be made betwixt a <hi>Subverter</hi> and a <hi>Continual Fruſtrater</hi> of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary Conſtitution.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt place, that <hi>Speech</hi> tells the Lords, that the <hi>All</hi> of their Lordſhips was <hi>at Stake,</hi> in that Buſineſs of <hi>Shirley;</hi> as if the Houſe of Peers could not ſtand unleſs they reſolved to hear him that Minute: and yet many Lords (if Prints belie them not) did ſeem to believe it. But thoſe Lords (I ſuppoſe) cannot but by this time obſerve this one Paſſage of the Print <hi>(Page</hi> the <hi>5th)</hi> which repreſents my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar that a Vote might paſs there, for medling <hi>with no private Buſineſs for ſix weeks. O my Lords,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>if this be your Buſineſs, ſee where you are, if we are to Poſtpone our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r the fear of Offending the Houſe of Commons, for ſix Weeks, they in the Interim may paſs the</hi> MONEY, <hi>and other acceptable Bills, which His Majeſty thinks of Importance.</hi> Sure the Print hath bely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ſo <hi>Loyal a Heart,</hi> as my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> to make him ſpeak thus: which in plain Engliſh amounts to this; <hi>[My Lords, take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eed what you do, the King longs to have the Bill about Money, and the other acceptable Bills of Importance dispatched, and brought to him; and the Houſe of Commons would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> have</hi> Shirley<hi>'s Buſineſs laid aſide for ſix Weeks, that the Work may not be hindred, but the King ſatisfied.]</hi> As if it had been a matter of Danger to ſatisfie the King; which is a Reflection upon Majeſty, not to be darted out by any Subject in ſo great an Aſſembly: And by it, you have the purpoſe of the great Deſign pointed out in moſt Legible Characters; his Lordſhip openly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Peers, if he can, to thwart the King, and render the Parliament unfit to do the Kings Buſineſs: So that if the Print be a true Copy of his Speech, then here's the Trouble-Houſe; <hi>Ex ore tuo condemnaberis.</hi> What need we any more witneſs who it is that troubles the King and Kingdom?</p>
                  <p>But the Print goes on, and ſaith his Lordſhip ſaid further: That to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſweet <hi>Shirley</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104590:15"/>
aſide <hi>(Page</hi> the <hi>6th) would be to alter the Conſtitution of the Government: and there is no Reaſon of State can be an Argument to your Lordſhips, to turn your ſelves out of that Intereſt you have in the Conſtitution of the Government.</hi> Nothing may more make us ſuſpect this Speech than that it preſents his Lordſhip as a Man afraid of altering the Conſtitution of Government. I muſt confeſs I never knew him like an alteration in any Government, as long as himſelf could be one in it: therefore ſeeing he is none now, 'tis wiſely done of him to inſinuate the Crime upon others; for, ſo the Print doth very ſlily upon thoſe Noble Lords, whoſe Judgment and Conſcience led them to lay aſide Diſputes about Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, that they might do the King and Kingdoms Buſineſs before <hi>Shirley</hi>'s: And for this they were told <hi>(Page 6th)</hi> that they were ready to give away their Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rage, with its Rights and Priviledges; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umbling down their own Houſe, to become Creatures as mean and low, notwithſtanding they have Titles, <hi>as they are in abſolute Monarchies: And, that there is no Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e that ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r Govern'd without a</hi> Nobility, <hi>or an</hi> Army: <hi>if you will not have one, you muſt have t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> other.</hi> And, thus he concludes, <hi>[I therefore declare, that I will ſerve my Prince as a Peer, but will not deſtroy the Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rage to ſerve him.]</hi> And now let us conſider, what occaſion or need his Lordſhip had of this high Bravade, unleſs it were craftily to poſſeſs mens Minds with a ſecret Opinion, as if the King and thoſe Noble Lords, which ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uck cloſe to His Majeſties Concerns, and the Kingdoms, in this Debate, had an end to <hi>Overthrow the Houſe of Peers,</hi> make the Monarchy <hi>abſolute,</hi> and Rule by an <hi>Army:</hi> A thing the moſt impertinently, and ſenſleſly inſinuated that can be, from ſuch Premiſes as have been mentioned. And it rather argues, that the Arguer hath ſome ſtrange deſign or other upon the Government, if he cannot by hook or by crook get him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in again to the Helm of it; But, his Reaſons and the Deſign being well enough ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, this, and ſome other little Deluſions, of late years practiſed under Publick good Pretences, cannot but be underſtood by the Lords and Commons, as meer Tricks to turn the Frame of Government off its Wheels again, and to ſhatter it into a <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Ariſtocratick, or a Popular Tyranny:</hi> for, that is the inevitable conſequence of unhinging this <hi>Well-order'd-Monarchy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, the <hi>Print</hi> ſaith, his Lordſhip went yet farther, being reſolved to ſearch the Monarchy to the bottom, <hi>page</hi> 10. and 11. and, by the way he digs down as low as the Grave of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud.</hi> His Lordſhips Friends of Presbytery tumbled him in, and, Why ſhould not he make bold to rake him out again? The new <hi>Canons</hi> alſo made in that Archbiſhops time are brought forth and Arraigned, with the Biſhops, for aſſerting Monarchy to be of <hi>Divine Right.</hi> It ſeems then the Work is going on again: they mean to bait the Biſhops, and undreſs the Monarchy once more, and then ſtuff it with Presbyterian Hay or Stubble. It may amaze any man to think of his Lordſhips wild way of diſcourſe; how it was poſſible, from ſo ſlender a Topick as the Caſe of <hi>Shirley,</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it unto the introducing and determining of ſo many great and weighty Points; and how he had the Art to hale them in thus by head and ſhoulders: but, the itch of much Speech-making is a diſeaſe that makes men ſometimes delirious. For, the <hi>Print</hi> boldly infers theſe following Particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That the King is King by Law, and by the ſame Law that the poor man enjoys his Cottage.</hi> What need this have been ſaid, at a time when there was no occaſion for it, unleſs his Lordſhip had a mind to maintain, That the King hath no Right more Divine than a Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tager? For, <hi>Dolus latet in Generalibus;</hi> and theſe things do not portend any good mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That a King Governing by an Aymy, without his Parliament, is a Government</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I own not, am not obliged to, nor was born under.</hi> 'Tis a pleaſant thing to have thus entertained the Houſe of Peers; Firſt with ſetting up <hi>Men of Straw,</hi> and then to defeat them; ſtart <hi>Chim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>raes, and run them down again;</hi> by force of imagination to ſix a King, as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104590:15"/>
Governing in the head of an imaginary Army, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>out him: and, the <hi>Scene</hi> of all this muſt be ſuppoſed to be <hi>England,</hi> becauſe his Lordſhip was not born, nor is obliged to Government any where elſe: Nor can the common Readers of his <hi>printed Speech</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, but that he means, and would ſeem to fear, all this in <hi>England;</hi> to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe elſe can ſo wiſe a <hi>Lord</hi> be thought to make ſo ſerious and eager a Proteſtation againſt it? or to what purpoſe elſe was it ſo carefully made publick <hi>in print,</hi> but that it was the ready way to get the World to underſtand it ſo? and that ſeems the ſole drift of the zeal of theſe impertinent excurſions. But yet he goes on.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e cannot find that the Jeſuites, or Popiſh Clergy ever owned Monarchy to be of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right; but onely ſome Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>opal clergy of our Briti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h Iſles.</hi> Then the Epiſcopal Clergy are (it ſeems) the better Subjects in a Monarchy. As for the <hi>two ſorts of Jeſuites,</hi> the <hi>Popi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h One,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> the former will not allow it to the Monarch, becauſe he would leave a gap open for the <hi>Popes</hi> Claim over Him<hi>:</hi> the latter alſo is of the ſame mind, becauſe he would ſubject Him to his <hi>Presbytery.</hi> There needs no reaſoning to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince theſe things, ſeeing there are few men in our age, who have not ſeen the truth <hi>in facto:</hi> ſo that 'tis the clear intereſt of the Crown, That if it will have a Church National to Govern by, it muſt be <hi>Proteſtant-Epiſcopal;</hi> otherwiſe its ſelf cannot be ſecure from the Invaſions and Inſolencies of the Pope on the one ſide, or of the <hi>Many-headed Presbyter</hi> on the other.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>That to ſay this Family are our Kings, and this particular Frame of Government is our Lawful Conſtitution, and obligeth us, is owing onely to the particular Laws of our Countrey.</hi> Well urged <hi>in print,</hi> my <hi>Lord,</hi> here is a fair Gap laid open for another Family, and another ſort of Government. And Why? The reaſon is plain, becauſe 'tis poſſible we may have other laws. Let but the Game go on, <hi>the Men of Shaftsbury,</hi> if they get it, will ſoon ſhew us that the <hi>Laws</hi> alſo may be changed; and then what may become of the Frame of Government? And what may become of the Family, if it ſhall not give way to the alteration of the old Laws and Government? He that makes a Crown to have no other Foundation but particular Laws, ought firſt, in a Monarchy, to ſhew me whence thoſe particular Laws could come, but from the Crown and him that firſt wore it: Law and popular Conſent came in afterward; not to conſtitute, but to confirm and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborate it on his head. I find, after long Obſervation and Experience of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, 'tis among all our <hi>State-Hereticks</hi> and Spurious Politicians, an <hi>Errour in Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> which leads them to diſpute with Crowned Heads, and that boldneſs prepares them to rebel; that they will needs ſuppoſe in the Original of Monarchy, a <hi>Priority of Laws</hi> to make it ſuch. As to <hi>Fact,</hi> the Hiſtories of Nations in general do conſute that <hi>vain Hypotheſis,</hi> upon which all their Arguments are built; and do ſhew, that for the moſt part Laws about Monarchy came in <hi>after its Inſtitution,</hi> to ſecond it by the peoples <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative Conſent:</hi> Not that this gave it any Authority, but their Aſſent to the Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, was onely a Signal of their ſubmiſſion and obedience to it. And as it was thus in the beginning of Monarchies, ſo, as to the Reaſon of the Point, it holds much the more ſtrongly againſt them in <hi>Monarchies already Conſtituted;</hi> for, there, no Law can be ſuppoſed <hi>Prior</hi> to the Monarch, becauſe they all ſlow from him, and cannot have being without him. Therefore that Mans Allegiance ſtands upon very ſlippery and uncertain Terms, who concludes the King and his Family, and their Rights, as meer Creatures of ſome particular Laws of the Countrey, and prints this Doctrine to the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to beget in them mean thoughts of that Royal Right to the Crown Imperial of this Realm, which is naturally inherent in his <hi>very Bloud,</hi> and <hi>Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Family;</hi> and cannot in a <hi>true Engliſh Political Sence</hi> be otherwiſe conſider'd: So that if ever his Lordſhips Notion be ſtarted again among the Peers, 'tis like it may, in that Houſe, meet with an <hi>Animadverſion</hi> much more ſevere than mine.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104590:16"/>
5. Nevertheleſs, the Print goes on very roundly in the Name of his Lordſhip, and ſaith, <hi>(Page</hi> 11.) <hi>If the Doctrine of the Divine Right of Monarchy be true, then our</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gna Charta <hi>is of no uſe, our Laws are but Rules during the Kings Pleaſure. Monarchy, if of Divine Right, cannot be bounded or limited by Humane Laws; nay, what's more, cannot bind it ſelf. All our Claims of Right, the Rights of the Peers Houſe, and of the Commons Houſe, and of all People, muſt give way to the Intereſt, and will and pleaſure of the Crown; and the beſt Men muſt Vote to deliver up all we have, not onely when Reaſon of State, and the ſeparate Intereſt of the Crown require it, but when 'tis known the will and pleaſure of the King would have it ſo. For, that muſt be to a Man of that Principle, the only Rule and Meaſure of Right and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.—</hi>Excellent <hi>State-Logick</hi> this! and were it my Aim to pervert the people, I would thus chop Allegiance into a thouſand Niceties, as the School-men do Divinity, for making ſuch like Inferences, to intoxicate the peoples minds; for, the Scripture makes Witchcraft near of kin to Rebellion; they ſeldom part company: and the Vilany inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by ſuch Arguments, is uſually maſqued and hid in ambiguous phraſes. What ado is here made with the word <hi>Divine Right!</hi> It may be remembred, the ſame was made uſe of to purpoſe by the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to inflame people into the former Rebellion. We would fain forget all their paſt <hi>Intrigues;</hi> but it ſeems there is freſh uſe of them; or elſe theſe thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s had not been thus boldly conjured up again into the <hi>Houſe of Peers;</hi> a place too ſacred for ſuch diſcourſes. In all Debates about the high Points of Polity, every Expreſſion ought not only to be ſeaſon'd by the Speaker, <hi>cum grano Salis;</hi> but to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood ſo alſo by the Hearers. If among Men of honeſt and fair intentions towards the King, it be ſaid the King holds his Monarchy <hi>by a Divine Right,</hi> none but a Mad-man, or a Man of deſign; a Man whoſe Buſineſs 'tis to catch at words, and cramp them with Commentaries to his own purpoſe; a Man that can blow up <hi>Mol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hills to Mountains;</hi> who carries a <hi>Microſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ope</hi> in his Pocket upon occaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, <hi>to ſee all in great;</hi> who, when he pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>ſtrains at G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ats in State,</hi> while he is out of Government; but can <hi>ſwallow Camels</hi> when he is in it; none but ſuch a Man would preſently conclude, that ſuch a <hi>Divine Right</hi> was meant, as excludes all bounding or limitation by Humane Laws; ſuch a One as leaves no Obligation from the Prince to the People. A Father hath a Divine Right to Rule his Son, and a Maſter his Servant; elſe the Scripture had never made Divine Injunctions, inveſting them with Rights of abſolute Power over them; and yet the ſame Scripture alſo ſignifies, that notwithſtanding thoſe Rights are <hi>Divine,</hi> there are Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations alſo upon the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> to the <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Servant.</hi> Such a Paternal abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Divine Right it is, that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have claimed and exerciſed over their Subjects, as that in all times <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>x cucurrit,</hi> the Laws have generally run in courſe, for preſervation of all the Rights and Liberties of the People, as well as thoſe of the Crown.</p>
                  <p>Now you ſee the <hi>Fox un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſed:</hi> the word <hi>Divine Right of Monarchy,</hi> is no ſuch Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear as we are told here in Print. And doubtleſs, the Lords and the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> all people both great and ſmall, will well conſider, that as this kind of Diſcourſe was haled into the <hi>Lords Houſe</hi> upon no occaſion, to ſerve ſome ends; ſo it was moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly timed, to bring it forth in the Reign of ſuch a King, whoſe tenderneſs towards the Laws and Liberties of the people hath been moſt remarkable in all his Actions. And if any thing that hath a Face of Power or Force extraordinary, or unuſual in the times of his Predeceſſors, hath appeared about him, 'tis no more than what theſe Fifteen years paſt hath been continued, and never found fault with by his <hi>then Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hip,</hi> but judged abſolutely neceſſary for his Guard and Defence againſt his <hi>now Lordſhips</hi> new Friends of Presbytery; the Irreconcileable Enemies, not only of this, but any King; becauſe the very Conſtitutio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Natural Temper of that Faction, renders them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with the Nature of his Crown and Dignity: Yet none ſhall more kiſs him,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104590:16"/>
and in kiſſing none more diminiſh him. Nor can there be imagined greater Enemies to all the reſt of his people; not only becauſe their deſign is ſpurred on with a Religious Zeal of Domination over their Fellow-ſubjects; but becauſe alſo their Machinations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtleſs and perpetual to graſp the Power, they neceſſitate the King, for defending his own Station, and his other peoples, to become the more heavy in his demands of Supply, to ſuſtain the Government againſt ſuch Domeſtick Adverſaries. And if ever the Excellent Form of it happen to be ſpoiled, (which God forbid) we muſt owe it to that ſort of Men; who have always made it their buſineſs to create Parties, and <hi>tell Noſes</hi> in both Houſes, and <hi>ſtart ſuch Hares as can never be run down;</hi> ſo that there might be neither time nor room to handle, or make an end of the important Affairs of the Kingdom; and what is this but to deſtroy the Exerciſe, Uſe, and publick End of Parliaments in <hi>England?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Print</hi> hath not done yet. <hi>Shirley</hi>'s Cauſe hath drawn hither alſo the whole Buſineſs of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland. We owe</hi> (it ſaith) <hi>the two laſt years Peace</hi> (by that it means the Peace we have with the <hi>Dutch) to the two Houſes differing from the ſence and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of</hi> White-Hall: And it ſaith his Lordſhip ſaid, 'tis a thing to be prayed for; that there may be <hi>no general Peace made with</hi> France; and that <hi>he himſelf would adviſe againſt it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>—Quantum mutatus ab illo!</q>
                  <p>See how conſiſtent his Lordſhip is with himſelf! Even as he was wont to be. Time was when he was an Adviſer at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and he could be of their ſence then, and took pains alſo to bring the Houſes to it.</p>
                  <p>As for example, When it was the ſence of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> that a War ought to be made with the <hi>Dutch;</hi> as glad as his Lordſhip now is of the Peace with them, he was at firſt as high as any Man againſt them; as appears by his Speech <hi>when he was Lord Chancellor,</hi> at the opening of the Seſſion of Parliament, 5 <hi>Febr.</hi> 1672. wherein he ſaid all he could to Inflame the Houſes againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> he reckon'd up their <hi>Perſonal Indignities to the King by Pictures and Medals, and other Publick Affronts from the States themſelves; their Breach of Treaties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oth in the</hi> Surinam <hi>and the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Buſineſs; their Height of Inſolence in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Honour and Right of the Flag, and disputing the Kings Title to it in all the Courts of</hi> Chriſtendom<hi>: and that they made great Offers to the</hi> French <hi>King, if He would ſtand by Them againſt Us: but the Moſt Chriſtian King too well remembred how dangerous a Neighbour they were to all Crowned Heads. That they were the Common Enemies to all Monarchies, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to Ours.</hi> And thereupon, as angry as he is now at our Kings fair carriage with the <hi>French,</hi> he then concluded it was well done to joyn Intereſts with the <hi>French King.</hi> And he told the Houſe then alſo, <hi>That at any rate</hi> Carthago eſt Delenda, <hi>the Hollanders were not onely to be brought down, but deſtroy'd.</hi> And further, to engage the Parliament to libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Supplies againſt them, he told the Houſes thus: <hi>'Tis your War; the King took his Meaſures from You, and they were Juſt and Right Ones. And if after this You ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r them to get up, let this be remembred, The States of</hi> Holland <hi>are</hi> England's <hi>eternal Enemy, both by Intereſt and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination.</hi> You ſee his Lordſhips Opinion then was, that the Parliament ought to bow to <hi>the Scene of Whitehall;</hi> but in a little time after, the <hi>Scene was altered;</hi> for no ſooner went his Lordſhip out of Office, but his Buſineſs was to bow the Houſes as much the other way; and with the ſame eagerneſs for a Peace with the <hi>Dutch</hi> againſt <hi>the Sence of Whitehall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Quo te teneam nodo mutantem Protea?</q>
                  <p>And in like manner he hath laboured to put the People out of humour with <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and ſet them againſt our being any way concerned with the <hi>French;</hi> telling the <hi>Lords</hi> in this Print, what a mighty dangerous Neighbour that King is grown to be. But the good People of <hi>England</hi> ought withal to conſider, That King did not in a Nights time
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104590:17"/>
grow up to this Magnitude. He was but little leſs at the time of his Lordſhips Greatneſs; yet all was well enough as long as his Lordſhip was great too; for then there was no cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of his about it, either in or out of Parliament: therefore miſtake not his preſent Peek and Indignation at the Court, for a zeal towards the Publick.</p>
                  <p>So I have done with that <hi>Speech</hi> to the Lords, Printed with the Name and Title of my Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> and now ye Men of <hi>Shaftsbury, what do ye think of him? Have ye not reaſon to be proud of ſo able a</hi> Speech-Maker? He's a brave Man indeed that can blow up a Parliament with a Breath, and a Kingdom into a Flame; but what wiſe Men are they that do not yet underſtand him! And what a Knave is he that thinks I mean the Earl of <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> to be the Man!</p>
                  <p>Now though I have done with the <hi>Speech,</hi> yet I cannot have done with the reſt of the Print; for I ſee Printed in the end of it another Buſineſs, in the Name of my good Lord <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> It is Intituled, <hi>The Proteſtation, with Reaſons of ſeveral Lords, for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of this Parliament; Entred in the Lords Journal,</hi> Novemb. 22. 1675. <hi>the day the Parliament was Prorogued.</hi> So that it ſeems his Lordſhip is not ignorant <hi>how this Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came on;</hi> nor can the World be ignorant how far his Hand went in promoting it; care having been taken by ſome Body during the time his Lordſhip was in the Country, before the laſt Seſſion of Parliament, to employ certain Emiſſaries and Agents, to carry up and down, not only to many Lords in and about this City, but likewiſe to all the moſt noted <hi>Coffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>-houſes,</hi> Copies of a <hi>Letter,</hi> ſaid in the Superſcription of it to have been firſt written to the Earl of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> and to have been ſubſcribed,</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Your Lordſhips humble Servant, SHAFTSBURY.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>My Lord of <hi>Carliſle</hi> is a very noble Perſon, and I would not by any means miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him, he having ſeen too many Experiments of <hi>Male-contented Demagogues,</hi> and their little Tricks, to be caught by them, or to countenance them. 'Tis rather to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Penner</hi> made bold with him. It was neceſſary to direct it to ſome Body, and eaſie to ſend Copies along with it, at the ſame time, to be communicated to every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; for there was no fear but among the <hi>Coffee-h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unters</hi> there would be found Copiers enough, to furniſh both City and Kingdom; the Deſign being laid now by this new Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to prepare Mens Minds for a crying down the preſent Parliament, ſeeing there are too many Wiſe Men in it, and too Loyal to be ſhaken by a <hi>Shuttlecock;</hi> and for crying out for a <hi>New Parliament,</hi> while in the mean time matters are ſo labour'd in the <hi>Old One</hi> (as we have abundantly ſeen the laſt Seſſion) that no Buſineſs ſhould be done by them; and then there may thence ariſe (as is imagined) an unanſwerable Argument for a Trial of Skill in Electing a <hi>New:</hi> for his Tool the Presbyter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing to get Dominion by the way of the King, wants only opportunity to be Canvaſing and Tugging for another <hi>Forty-One-Parliament;</hi> and would never be at reſt, till he hath gotten both Houſes over his Head again at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> So that if the other <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> will well apprehend the improvement of their own Intereſt, let them know, that as they have reaſon to decline them, being their worſt Enemies by principle; ſo they have the faireſt opportunity, in ſhewing themſelves firm henceforth to the Crown, to ſtand moſt fair in the good opinion and favour of His Majeſty, as a Party much more tolerable in the Conſtitution of the Government: And then there can be no fear of that they call Perſecution, becauſe the reaſon and occaſion of it will be gone. No Creditor but will be kind when he hath gotten <hi>Security.</hi> Even ſo it is with Kings, and other Governours: they grieve no Party more than other, when they are once ſecured they will pay the Debt of Obedience and Loyalty; for, 'tis their Intereſt to cheriſh, and ſee every Party thri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and flouriſh, if it be not dangerous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104590:17"/>
Arguments in that Epiſtle his Lordſhip offers none, having long ſince arrived to that Noble Confidence, as to think his own word ſufficient warrant for any Aſſertion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he boldly ſaith, 'tis the Intereſt of the King, the Lords, and the Commons, to have a <hi>New Parliament,</hi> without any more ado. But for his Reaſons, we muſt have recourſe to the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> it ſelf; which are firſt for the Diſſolution of this Parliament, and they are but theſe few following.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, The Proteſtation ſaith, <hi>It is according to the ancient Laws and Statutes of this Realm, that there ſhould be frequent and new Parliaments; and that the practiſe of ſeveral years hath been accordingly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis true, the Kings of this Realm have formerly had cauſe to delight in calling them, and our Chronicles tell us alſo, that till the <hi>Barons</hi> Wars came, and after the <hi>Barons</hi> Wars were ended, down to the time of King <hi>James,</hi> Parliaments were modeſt in their ſtation, and eaſie to the King; ſo that the Buſineſs of the Kingdom went on current: without long Speeches and hot Diſputes: But in King <hi>James</hi> his time, the <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Purita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> (as Men then called him) (whom Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in her time, not without much ado kept down) began to ſpread his Wings, grew numerous and headſtrong, ſo that they were able to furniſh the Commons Houſe with a <hi>Canvaſing Party,</hi> and did it conſtantly at every Election; and divers Members of the Houſe of Peers, who in thoſe days affected Preferment at Court, and wanted it, and envied others that had it, or were otherwiſe male-content, or intoxicated with miſtaken Zeal of new Phantſies about Religion, or Church-Government, were not wanting to make a <hi>Party of Lords,</hi> to ſecond that <hi>fiery part</hi> of the <hi>Commons;</hi> who carried matters divers times ſo high, that That King was neceſſitated, towards the latter end of his Reign, for the Honour of his Crown, and Preſervation of the Government in q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iet, often to diſſolve them: Of which the Puritan (that is, the Presbyter) always made advantage by exceeding Clamour againſt the Court, to gain the ignorant and unwary part of the people to his party. And ſo you ſee to what ſort of Men we owe the new invention of <hi>Fruſtrating Parliaments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this comes King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt to the Government, upon whom they perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually practis'd it in all Parliaments that he called; and at length (you know) that working upon the Kings Neceſſities in the year 1641. they in a manner conſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned him to perpetuate them in Power; which was the ruine of the Royal Government, and at length of all Government it ſelf. It is to be noted alſo, that it was not till the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Reign, that they took up the other <hi>New Trick of State;</hi> which was, ſeeing they durſt not yet be ſo bold, as to ſtrike at the King himſelf for ſuppoſed defaults in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they reſolved to ſtrike as near him as they could; and ſo they began to make it conſtant work, to fall upon his <hi>Chief Miniſters of State;</hi> and always, in the Intervals of Parliament, made it their Buſineſs to fill the Kingdom with Clamours againſt them; ſo preparing them thereby, as a Sacrifice to their own ends and cruelty, and to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples folly, againſt every call of a Parliament. Thus it was from the time of the old Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> (who by a brave Defence in Parliament made good his Station) to the time of that moſt brave, though moſt unfortunate Man, the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> whom they <hi>worried</hi> to death by <hi>Popular Tumults,</hi> after he had baſtled them at the Bar in defending himſelf moſt gloriouſly: As they did alſo Archbiſhop <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d,</hi> a Man of high deſign for the Honour of the King, and Glory of the Church; which they charged on him to be for introducing of Slavery and Popery; ſo that all the reſt of the King's Miniſters were glad to flee for ſafety of their Lives. Nay, they ſtopt not here; but being fluſht, drew up Articles of High Treaſon againſt the <hi>Queens Majeſty.</hi> And then, we too ſadly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, how eaſily afterwards they paſſed on to a Charge againſt the King himſelf.</p>
                  <p>I write not this, as if I meant to ſcandalize, or caſt an <hi>Odium</hi> upon that ancient Right and Liberty of Parliaments, to Inſpect the Actions and Behaviour of the great Officers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104590:18"/>
of Truſt, and call them to account, if faulty; it being confeſſed a good advantage and ſecurity to the King and Kingdom, and neceſſary to be continued: but my purpoſe here is onely to note, when and how the Abuſe of that Parliamentary Power, and by what Faction it was firſt made ſo extravagant, that no ſooner could a Favourite or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of State be warm in his Office, or in the Kings Favour, and had reſolved to look ſtrictly to a maintaining the Rights and Conſtitution of Government in Church and State, but immediately they fell upon the Back of him, and gave out the word for his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing, or his Deſtruction. No doubt but the beſt of Men in great place will have Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Faults, being more then other Men diſtracted with many Buſineſſes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to many Temptations, as the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> ſaid at his Tryal; but that they ſhould by Popular Breath and Faction be blown up to the degree of high Crime or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when they have perhaps, in the Judgment of Men moderate and wiſe, onely ſerved the King with the beſt of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kill; this is both uncharitable, and cruel; or the effect of Faction, or Envy; and it is this onely that I redargue: for, it is in a factious time, the great Intereſt of the Crown to ſee to it, and to nip this Grand Abuſe whenever it ſhall be practiſed; always taking due meaſure between a juſt or conſcionable, and a factious proſecution. Elſe theſe Inconveniences will follow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As 'tis in the Nature of Man to be well-con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eited of himſelf,</hi> (otherwiſe moſt Men would even hang themſelves) <hi>ſo generally a ſecret Envy ariſes in him at the preferment of another, becauſe he thinks he deſerves better than he; and the King preſently gets his ill-will for paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him by. This Man then meets with many other of his own ſence and humour; and ſo by rubbing each others Sores till they ſmart, they reſolve preſently, that the</hi> Preferree <hi>is a Common Enemy, and as ſuch to fall upon him: And ſo the Iſſue at laſt ſhall be this, when the courſe of Accuſation grows cuſtomary, that the King ſhall never be free of his own Choice, nor ſecure of his Miniſters, when he hath choſen them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen to be preferr'd ſhall be to be expoſed, and ſhot at by all the Darts of Envy and Danger, what Man of Wiſdom or Fortune will be willing to accept of Preferment? or be true and tight to the Kings Concern and Intereſt in the Government, if he do accept it? Or will he not rather be tempted through fear of that</hi> Accuſatory Faction, <hi>to ſerve the Regal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt but by halves? or perhaps to betray his Maſters Government in Church and State, (as ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me did in the time of the Kings Father, when they ſaw him forced to leave</hi> Strafford) <hi>to make a Friend of that Faction? For, thus Men will be too apt to do when they cannot be ſure of their Maſters. So that if Kings once quit their Conſtancy in this particular, nothing brings greater hazard to their own Intereſt of Government, and their Perſons; nor greater diminution to the Kingly Dignity and Power, in the opinion of other Princes; while his Miniſters and himſelf ſhall remain liable to be baited, at every turn of humour, by ſo buſie and impetuous a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: as if himſelf were not wiſe enough to chuſe, or as if we had none but Knaves in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be choſen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally, <hi>'Tis, and ought ever to be, an</hi> Arcanum <hi>kept, as the Jewels are, in the Royal Cabinet, to preſerve all places which are nigh the Throne, ſo ſacred as not to be eaſily invaded; for that draws a Reverence to the Throne it ſelf; which ſhould be religiouſly fenced about, not only as the Sacrary of Royalty, but as the Sanctuary alſo of other Princes; for, ſuch are his great Men, and high Officers of State in their places: They are as the Lyons about the Throne of</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, <hi>to beget a dread and ſence of Majeſty in all that approach to it: and thoſe are not Beaſts for Sacrifice, nor to be offer'd up as ſuch, nor to be pull'd down without very great cauſe of Juſtice require it; becauſe the frequency of pulling down the Fence, hardens Men; and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them by cuſtom ſo hardy, as to make bold with the Throne it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This licentious Abuſe of criminating the Kings Miniſters, hath by the ſame Faction
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104590:18"/>
which firſt began it, been carried of late times to ſuch a height, that were a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reputed never ſo honeſt, yet no ſooner doth the King make him one of his great Officers, but that if he ſticks cloſe to his Maſters Intereſt of Government, he preſently becomes a publick Enemy; and as ſuch they brand him and teaze him, and ſeek to tire out his Majeſty with Importunities and Addreſſes to be rid of him. This ſort of Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was the reaſon which made his Majeſties <hi>Grandfather</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> not ſo frequent in calling Parliaments; and the <hi>Proteſting Lords</hi> may do well to conſider, how little reaſon their Son, His preſent Majeſty, is like to have, to become fond of <hi>New Parliaments,</hi> till he can have ſome good ground to believe, that they will return to the like temper and moderation, as they had in old time, when thoſe ancient Laws and Statutes for frequent calling them were made: or until the people ſee their errour at Elections, in ſuffering Men of that implacable Faction, which firſt poyſon'd the fair ſtream of Parliamentary Duty, ſtill to creep into the Houſe, to ſhelter themſelves in acting their miſchievous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, under the Covert of Priviledge of Parliament, and publick good.—So I have done with their Lordſhips Firſt Reaſon in the <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> and proceed to the <hi>Second,</hi> which is this.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>It ſeems not reaſonable, that any particular number of men ſhould, for many years, ingroſs ſo great a truſt of the People, as to be their Repreſentatives in the Houſe of Commons,</hi> and as good men as theſe <hi>Members of the Counties and Corporporations, be ſo long excluded.</hi> This kind of reaſoning I never expected from the mouths of ſuch Noble Lords. Nay, then (methinks) I ſee <hi>John Lilburn</hi> putting on Robes, and uttering his old Oracles of State. What! <hi>Is there no Smith to be found in Iſrael,</hi> to whet Arguments for their Lordſhips, that they are fain to go down to him, and his <hi>Philiſtines</hi> the <hi>Levellers?</hi> for, thus they argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nigh Thirty years ago againſt the then Houſe of Commons: and good my Lords re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that the ſame Argument being but a very little altered, ſerved alſo at that time againſt the Houſe of <hi>Peers.</hi> Be informed, my noble Lords, you whoſe names I find in a <hi>Catalogue</hi> Printed at the end of this <hi>Proteſtation;</hi> for ye cannot (I ſuppoſe) remember, becauſe when I read your <hi>Names,</hi> I perceive that none of you were then <hi>Sitters</hi> in the Lords Houſe, except one, whoſe name I forbear; as I do the names of all the reſt, beſide my good Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> who in thoſe dayes was <hi>ubiquitarian:</hi> therefore doubtleſs he could have inform'd your Lordſhips, as well as I, of what then paſſed in publick, if it had been to his purpoſe that you ſhould have had this informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before you were thus far tranſported, and your names cunningly proclaimed in Print; which queſtionleſs was done, in hope that it may be a means to faſten and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you deeper.</p>
                  <p>But I ſay again (my Lords) <hi>be informed,</hi> and conſider, that it was the general Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Lillurn,</hi> and all the <hi>Levellers, that it ſuited not with the freedom and Intereſt of the people of</hi> England, <hi>That ſome men ſhould continue long in Publick Truſt and Power as the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Repreſentatives, ſeeing the reſt of the people had as much right to govern as they, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to have a turn as well as they in the Government.</hi> And for ſuch a turn alſo they were in the Government of the then Army; they were for turning out all the General Officers and Colonels; and the common ſoldiers were taught to demand Rule by turns; and the clamor for it was ſo high, that <hi>Cromwell</hi> could by no means quiet them, till he gave way that they ſhould, in every Regiment, chuſe one private ſoldier to appear for all his Fellows, to ſit and conſult in the General Council of Officers. And all this was urged and extorted, by uſing the ſame Argument of an equal Right in the Commons to come into place of Government, one as well as another.</p>
                  <p>Nay, Further (my Lords) it may be remembred, this brave way of Arguing did not reſt here; it did not only, at that time, trouble and ſhake the Commons-Houſe, but a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104590:19"/>
little after it was improved to a demoliſhing of your own. From a Clamouring againſt Commons continuing long in Power, they proceeded to do the like againſt all <hi>ſtanding Powers</hi> whatſoever; ſo that of courſe they caſt their eyes next at the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> and the like Argument ſerved to purpoſe againſt them, as a Power of <hi>long continuance,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect at all to their Birth-right. As for the reſt of their <hi>Levelling Reaſons,</hi> I had rather bury than repeat them. For, it is my great grief to live to ſee any Lords, to when the Weapons of Diſcourſe upon the <hi>Anvile of the Levellers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But yet their <hi>Protesting Lordſhips</hi> go on thus:</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>The long Continuance of ſuch as are intruſted for others, and who have ſo great a power over the Purſe of the Nation, muſt, in our humble opinion, naturally endanger the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Factions and Parties, and the carrying on of particular Intereſts and Deſigns, rather than the publick Good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This their <hi>Third Reaſon</hi> being the laſt, is alſo an <hi>Arrow</hi> that was formerly ſhot out of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>velling Quiver</hi> againſt their Lordſhips. They abundantly argued againſt the Commons; that <hi>long continuance of men in power and truſt, and all ſtanding powers what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, were like standing waters, they naturally corrupt, and produce Factions and Parties for particular ends and deſigns, and mind not the Publick Good.</hi> I could here inject Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations too many out of their Publiſhed Papers, to ſhew their Lordſhips, how ſmartly they argued alſo with the ſame kind of Sophiſtry for the utter ſubverſion of the Houſe of Peers, alledging, <hi>that they were but men as well as others, and ſubject to the ſame frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo, being continually in power, were as likely to produce Factions, and drive particular Intereſts and Ends to the prejudice of the Publick; and judged that they did ſo in thoſe dayes, when a Party of Lords ſtrook in with a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party in the Commons Houſe, againſt the publick Intereſt and good of the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Levellers;</hi> who had arrogated unto themſelves the name of <hi>The Publick,</hi> and <hi>The People,</hi> and <hi>The Nation.</hi> The having the <hi>Purſe</hi> of the Nation long, as the Commons have; or a place of conſtant power over the Nation, as the Lords have by Birth-right, doth not alter the caſe in this way of Argumentation, becauſe any men may be corrupt and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the uſe and exerciſe of either. Therefore theſe their Lordſhips ('tis hoped) will be <hi>humble in Opinion</hi> hereafter, about the matter of diſſolving this Houſe of Commons, and calling a <hi>New One,</hi> and not fall on a ſudden to <hi>Proteſting,</hi> till they ſee better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons than what are borrowed from their old <hi>Levelling Enemies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly, my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> if he had pleaſed, might have furniſhed his fellow-Proteſting Friends and himſelf before he Signed that <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> with reaſons of another ſtrain, and thoſe out of his own ſtock too; for it appears, he hath been a much more rational perſon; but, it was before he loſt his Places at Court; and truly, ſeeing a loſs of ſo much Honor and Profit is enough to tap any man out of Tune, and put him into paſſion, we ought to give allowance for humane infirmity, and excuſe his weak memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For, his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> might have remembred he was of another Opinion; and that was not long ſince, when he was <hi>Lord Chancellor,</hi> in his fore-cited Speech to the <hi>Lords and Commons,</hi> at the Opening of a Seſſion of Parliament, 1672, where you had his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> in a Fit of Great Devotion, offering a Sacrifice of Thanks and Praiſe to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for ſuch a King, and ſuch a Parliament, and for ſuch happy times of Peace and Plenty: which, for the Honor of his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> or rather of the King and this <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſhall here be repeated. The Words are theſe,</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>[After His Majeſties Concluſion of His Speech, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t me conclude, nay let us all conclude with bleſſing God, and the King. Let us bleſs God, that he hath given us ſuch a King, to be the Repairer of our breaches, and the Reſtorer of our paths to dwell in:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104590:19"/>
                        <hi>That in the midst of War and Miſery, which rages in our Neighbor-Countries,</hi> our Garners are full, and there is no complaining in our ſtreets: <hi>and a man can hardly know there is a War.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let us bleſs God, that he hath given this King ſignally the hearts of His people, and moſt particularly of this Parliament, who in their affection and Loyalty to their Prince, have exceeded all their Predeceſſors. A Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt, with whom the King hath many years lived with all the Careſſes of a happy Marriage. Has the King had a Concern? you have wedded it. Has His Majesty wanted Supplies? you have readily, cheerfully, and fully provided for them; you have relied upon the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Conduct of His Majeſty in all His Affairs; ſo that you have never attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to exceed your Bounds, or to impoſe upon Him; whilſt the King, on the other hand, hath made your Counſels the foundations of all His proceedings: and hath been ſo tender of you, that He hath, upon His own Revenue and Credit, endeavoured to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port even Foreign Wars, that He might be leaſt uneaſie to you, or burdenſom to His people.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And let me ſay, That though this Marriage be according to</hi> Moſes's <hi>LAW, where the Husband can give a Bill of Divorce, put her away, and take another: yet</hi> I CAN ASSURE YOU, <hi>it is as impoſſible for the King to part with this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is for you to depart from that Loyalty, Affection, and Dutiful Behaviour, you have hitherto ſhewed towards Him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let us bleſs the King for taking away all our Fears, and leaving no room for Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: for thoſe Aſſurances and Promiſes He hath made us. Let us bleſs God and the King, that our Religion is ſafe: That the</hi> CHURCH OF ENGLAND <hi>is the Care of our Prince: That</hi> PARLIAMENTS ARE SAFE<hi>: That our</hi> properties <hi>and</hi> liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>are ſafe. What more hath a good</hi> Engliſhman <hi>to ask, but that this King may long Reign; and that this triple Alliance of King, Parliament, and People, may never be DISSOLVED?]</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>All which being ſpoken of this preſent Parliament; may well ſerve for an Anſwer to his Lordſhips <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> notwithſtanding thoſe Reaſons therein contained: For ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, matters cannot in ſo ſhort a time be ſo exceedingly alter'd, as to deſerve this <hi>proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or the declaimings, in that violent manner, (as throughout this whole Diſcourſe we have ſeen) by reflecting upon the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and againſt the continuance of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> that were, in his Lordſhips good opinion, ſo ſacred about five years ago. The old ſaying is,<hi>—Nemo repente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it turpiſſimus—;</hi> and 'tis a true one, that <hi>no man grows as bad as bad may be on a ſudden:</hi> and if there be any weight in what his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath ſaid on both ſides, it is more reaſonable and probable for us to conclude and underſtand ill of himſelf, rather than of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Tranſits</hi> of great Aſſemblies are not ſo quick: and another Proverb ſaith, <hi>Great Bodies move but ſlowly,</hi> ſo that their principles, purpoſes and deſigns, cannot vary all points of the Compaſs, at ſo briſk a rate as <hi>one nimble States-man</hi>'s, whoſe motion is wont to be <hi>per Saltum,</hi> after the manner of <hi>Leap-Frog,</hi> from the <hi>Artick</hi> to the <hi>Antartick</hi> in a Trice; eſpecially if he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to fall into foul weather at Court, and can ride there no longer, but muſt make uſe of any wind to ſet ſail into ſome other Port. Which (we hope) will be conſider'd by the reſt of the <hi>Lords Proteſters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And truly, their Lordſhips have the fairer excuſe to come off, becauſe the thing was done in a heat, and in haſte; as appears firſt by the printed Title of the <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> which ſaith it was on the morning that the Parliament was Prorogued, 1675; and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted words at the end of it are, That the Lords in print, <hi>were all that were in the Houſe early enough to Sign it before the Prorogation:</hi> So that it ſeems his Lordſhip could not be at reſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104590:20"/>
till he had given all the World to underſtand, why it was that he was ſo warm in his Speeches upon Croſs-points, which muſt make a Breach betwixt the Houſes all along the Seſſion, to hinder all manner of publick Buſineſs; and then, from the non-diſpatch of it to in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er, that this Parliament is not fit for it; and then (forſooth) we are to believe what he dictates, and admit a <hi>proteſting Ergo;</hi> That there is a neceſſity of diſſolving this, and calling a <hi>new Parliament.</hi> For, his Lordſhip and the reſt in print do cloſe the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> with theſe three Lines; <hi>That it is in their humble opinion, become altogether unpracticable for the Two Houſes, as the caſe ſtands, joyntly to purſue thoſe great and good Ends for which they were called.</hi> That is as much as to ſay, it will be ſo, if the caſe ſhall ſo ſtand in the opening of this <hi>approching Seſſion,</hi> as it was in the ending of the laſt. For, ſome ſay his Lordſhip hath Dr. <hi>Shirley</hi> in his pocket, and can ſtart him again at pleaſure, to make the ſame ſcuffle about priviledge betwixt the Houſes. But ſome think he will be wiſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, becauſe the Trick being now thus plainly underſtood, it will be too ridiculous to play it over again, in an Aſſembly of ſo many noble, ſeeing and knowing Men, as make up the <hi>Houſe of Peers.</hi> Nor is it probable, that the <hi>Commons Houſe,</hi> filled with men of great wiſdom, inſight in Affairs, and integrity, ſhould meet together without Expedients to prevent further Conteſts, and to carry on the King and Kingdoms buſineſs. Which they are the rather obliged to do for the Honour of their Houſe, in a double reſpect: <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe if this Houſe of Commons, which began and carried on things ſo gloriouſly, for the Eſtabliſhment of the King, and Settlement of the Kingdom, ſhall be deprived of opportunity to finiſh what they began, What can be the end, but to go out <hi>in a Snuff?</hi> according to the Deſigns of a buſie <hi>Rampant Faction,</hi> who mortally hate them for the good they have done; and whoſe Triumph it would be, to tranſmit the memory of them to poſterity with ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ominy, and this bitter <hi>Sarcaſm: That they began to build, but could not make an end.—Secondly,</hi> They are exceedingly concerned in point of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſeeing they are repreſented in Print to the World, as a ſort of people that may be eaſily plaid upon, and led by the noſe to do what other men pleaſe. For, in a print publiſhed at the ſame time with the other prints, ſince the laſt Seſſion, and by the ſame hand, Entituled, <hi>The Debate or Arguments for Diſſolving this preſent Parliament, and the calling frequent New Ones: as they were delivered in the Houſe of Peers, Novemb.</hi> 20th. 1675. I find, <hi>page</hi> 9. <hi>it is boaſted by the Deſigners,</hi> concerning the Commons Houſe, <hi>that they have a party of Members in that Houſe,</hi> whom the ſaid print calls, <hi>Many of the ableſt and moſt worthy Patriots among them; whoſe</hi> buſineſs it was to ſecond the <hi>Proteſting Lords, by carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this difference betwixt the Houſes to the greateſt height, that by this means they might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Nation from this Parliament by Diſſolution, and have a New one called.</hi> So that Here we have OPEN CONFESSION, that it was a <hi>Deſign</hi> carried on by a <hi>PARTY</hi> in both Houſes, to bring on, and carry on their Fellow-Members to ſuch diſputes, as might Diſable them to do the Publick Work; and thence to conclude, that they ought to be diſſolved. Which certainly is a Conſpiracy of ſuch a Magnitude, that none ever exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it but the <hi>Powder-Treaſon:</hi> Eſpecially, if we conſider, what courſe hath been taken by this kind of Prints, ſpread over the Three Kingdoms, to Poiſon mens minds, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government Ridiculous, by expoſing the Debates and Conteſtings of Parliament to the Scorn and Contempt of the Vulgar, through the Artifice and cunning of that <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Party,</hi> which I have ſo often mentioned; and whoſe DESIGN is now Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, to be a BLOWING UP of the <hi>Parliament</hi> after another manner.</p>
                  <p>It cannot be amiſs therefore, before I diſmiſs this Point, to try the ſtrength of what they have DISCOURSED for a <hi>NEW PARLIAMENT,</hi> as it hath been Printed in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Pamphlet, called, <hi>The Debate and Arguments uſed in the Houſe of Peers,</hi> &amp;c. There are (ſaith that <hi>Pamphlet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Two Objections that make a great Sound, which have really nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of weight in them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:104590:20"/>
                     <hi>The firſt Objection is, That the Crown is in danger if you call a New Parliament.</hi> This Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection they pretend to anſwer, by ſaying, there's no fear of danger, becauſe Men of <hi>Quality, of Eſtates, and of the beſt Underſtanding, and ſuch as will give Money will be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</hi> But, I reply, this Argument hath more Malice than Reaſon to ſupport it, becauſe it reflects, as if theſe were not ſuch. The Generality of this Houſe of Commons are known to be men of the beſt Quality, and of Eſtates, and of the beſt underſtanding. All their Fault is, in the Opinion of the <hi>Conſpiring Party,</hi> that they too well underſtand them and their Deſign; and what the true intereſt of the Crown is, and that as they ever have been, ſo they ſtill are tight and firm to it, and the Government; and that the great intereſt of the Nobles, Gentry, and Commons of the Land lies in being ſo. This they underſtand: Beſides, they are men beſt acquainted and expert in the management of Parliamentary Affairs, and therefore more likely than men newly elected, to make diſpatch of them, if the <hi>Projectors</hi> did not ſtudy all ways to impede them, for other ends than the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſe and ſupply of the Crown. And therefore a New Parliament is not now to be called for theſe following Reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. Becauſe it is not for the honour of the King, to be as it were <hi>Trepann'd</hi> thus by Tricks, or worried by Clamors and Importunities, into a neceſſity of calling a new Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, becauſe it will, in the judgment of wiſe men at home, and of Princes abroad, be no other than <hi>an impoſing upon him</hi> in one main point of his <hi>Prerogative;</hi> which is, to uſe His own diſcretion, and take His own time, for the ſummoning and diſſolving of Parliaments.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. It cannot be for his ſafety or advantage, becauſe if Money be wanting, know, he muſt pay dear for it before the <hi>New One</hi> will give it: and, What can they give, which may not more readily be had by the preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> if the juſt indignation of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and His two Houſes ſhall ariſe againſt the ſtratagems o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Prime Projectors,</hi> and defeat them? I cannot forget what mine eyes have ſeen in the days of His Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; therefore, ſince <hi>years teach wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om;</hi> and the experience of like matters in time paſt, gives inſtruction for the future, it cannot but be good to bring them freſh into remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. Let us therefore remember how it was with King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt. It was the cunning of the ſame <hi>Faction,</hi> having an <hi>aking Tooth</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and conſequently a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to alter the Government, as now they have again; which they could not eaſily do without clamouring about matters of Religion; and againſt ſome Errors and Exceſſes, of the Court and the King's Miniſters; Therefore, as they plied that point home, in hope to gain the people; ſo, in the beginning of His Reign, they finding the King in neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Money to ſatisfie His Fathers Debts, and for other great occaſions at home and abroad; and knowing that a Parliament muſt be called for Raiſing Money, they laid the Plot thus: <hi>Firſt,</hi> to work upon that neceſſity by <hi>high popular demands,</hi> ſuch as muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bow the King to comply with them, and then it would be eaſie for them to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue their wild projects of alteration in State and Church; or elſe it would conſtrain him to break them: And that they feared not, knowing it could not be long before he would have occaſion to call a <hi>Second Parliament;</hi> which they, by the like demands, would bring to nothing as eaſily as before, unleſs the King would conſent to them: which they preſumed he would never do. And it came to paſs, as they had before contrived; that the King was fruſtrated of the hopes he had of three or four Parliaments, by ſending them away one after another, not getting one peny<hi>:</hi> but he being tired out, and having perceived that they entred upon ſuch debates, and made ſuch demands, as intrenched upon the Intereſt of His Crown, and that a condeſcenſion to them, would have brought both him and it into contempt; he was conſtrained to ſhift without Parliaments, to his great ſorrow; and it proved to be the great occaſion of the late War, enough to ſhew what it is for a King in want of Money, in theſe days, to call a New Parliament, of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104590:21"/>
whoſe kindneſs he hath had no experience; eſpecially when he hath already a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in being, moſt dutiful, wiſe, and able to do his and his Kingdoms buſineſs, if ſome few perſons would pleaſe to ſtudy peace, and leave off contention. The truth of the forementioned Plot of the Commons in thoſe days, I ſhall, by and by, more particularly demonſtrate.</p>
                  <p>In the mean while, you may remember, I told you, this ſort of Game they began in the latter end of the Reign of King <hi>James;</hi> and now you ſhall ſee how they plaid it. Before that time the Commons never medled at ſo high a rate; but in the Nineteenth year of that King, when he called a Parliament about the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Prince Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> his Majeſty was in great want of Money to relieve the <hi>Palatinate;</hi> and great hopes were given him of a Supply. What was the Iſſue of this neceſſity of calling it? The King had a mind to Adjourn the Parliament but for a little ſeaſon, and for ſome Reaſons which he foreſaw required it; whereupon the <hi>Faction</hi> preſently interpoſed, and drew the reſt of their Fellow-Members to Petition him againſt Adjournment: inſomuch that the wiſe King, being <hi>Jealous of his Prerogative,</hi> and not liking that the Commons ſhould ſo much as meddle with it, though in a way but Petitionary, he very much reſented it, and told a Committee which they ſent to him about it, That he <hi>took it very ill</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſhould diſpute his Reaſons of Adjournment, <hi>all Power being in him alone to Call, Adjourn, and Diſſolve Parliaments.</hi> This made the <hi>Faction</hi> ſo bold and Mutinous in diſcourſe every where, that His Maieſty was fain to put forth a Proclamation againſt talking of State-affairs with ſuch inordinate liberty.</p>
                  <p>The time of the Parliaments Adjournment being expired, they came together again; and what then? The <hi>Palatine Cauſe</hi> requiring Supply more than before; and the <hi>Lord Treaſurer</hi> having in a Speech laid open the Kings Wants, and how empty his Coffers were, the <hi>Faction</hi> thought they ſhould now in his Neceſſity be able to <hi>work him like Wax;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſtead of Money, they immediately ſalute him with a Catalogue of his Faults, the growing Miſchiefs of his Government, and dictate unto him Remedies; and they called it <hi>A Petition and Remonſtrance.</hi> The King then by Letter to the <hi>Speaker,</hi> ſharply com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of this Indignity, imputes it not to the Houſe it ſelf, but to the <hi>boldneſs of ſome fiery and popular Spirits in the Houſe of Commons,</hi> which were the Predeceſſors of our preſent <hi>Faction;</hi> whom he brands with <hi>Breach of his Prerogative Royal, by debating publickly Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which were above them.</hi> Nevertheleſs, having him at a pinch for Money, they grew the bolder; and hereupon drew up another <hi>Petition,</hi> and ſent it to back their former <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance.</hi> To which his Majeſty gave a <hi>ſmart Anſwer,</hi> taxing the <hi>Faction,</hi> and deſiring the Commons henceforth not to give car to <hi>thoſe Tribunitial Orators among them; adviſing them alſo to keep within their Bounds; and that the way to preſerve their Priviledges, was not to pare his Prerogative, and pull the Flowers of the Crown.—</hi>Then to ſhew it was indeed a <hi>Fiery Faction,</hi> they blew the Flame yet higher<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by Speech-making got the <hi>Major Vote</hi> to come to a <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> that they ought to debate high Matters, and it was their Priviledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this was done by the Faction, by ſurpriſe, the Third part of the Houſe not preſent. This ſo moved the King, that to preſerve his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> he was forced to ſend for the <hi>Clerk of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> to bring his Journal-Book to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and produce it in the <hi>Pricy Council,</hi> where his Majeſty thought fit, that the <hi>Proteſtation ſhould be razed out of all Memorials, and utterly to be annihilated, both in respect of the manner by which it was gained, and of the Matter therein contained:</hi> and he did in full Council, and in the preſence of the <hi>Judges,</hi> declare it void and of none effect, becauſe it was Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſuch general and ambiguous words, <hi>as might ſerve for future Times, to invade moſt of the Rights and Prerogatives annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm:</hi> For, his Majeſty did not deny, but that the Houſe might Treat and Debate <hi>De Arduis Regni,</hi> which words (ſaid the King) <hi>were cunningly mentioned in that Proteſtation: but they ought to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member'd</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104590:21"/>
                     <hi>alſo the word</hi> Quibuſdam, which reſtraineth the generality of the other words, <hi>Arduous Affairs of the Kingdom, to ſuch particular Caſes as his Majeſty pleaſeth to conſult with them upon.</hi> Therefore the King did further, <hi>Mann propria,</hi> take the ſaid Proteſtation out of the Journal-Book of the <hi>Cemmons,</hi> and made an <hi>Act of Council</hi> thereupon. And in ſix days after, he was neceſſitated to Diſſolve them, having got not one Peny of Money for his Extream Occaſions. For it was the <hi>Arcanum</hi> of the Faction even in thoſe days, to make <hi>High Demands,</hi> and raiſe <hi>Quarrels about Priviledges,</hi> and other Matters intrenching upon the <hi>Rights of the Crown;</hi> that as oft as they got the Parliament-Houſe over their Heads, they took the ſame Method of working upon <hi>want of Money,</hi> to brave the King; and by not ſupplying him, to held his <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to the Grindſtone.</hi> They clamour'd ever for Parliaments, lured the King in wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hopes of Money to call them, and then in ſtead of Money they fell to diſputing with him; ſo that the Parliaments in the latter end of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, were of no uſe to him, except the laſt, a little before he died: For, in his laſt appearance with them he complained, how the Faction had made him <hi>Break the Necks of Three Parliaments together:</hi> by which he meant the Three Preceding Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>James</hi> being gone, now let us ſee more at large how they uſed his Son King <hi>Charles,</hi> in his firſt Parliament <hi>Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1625. which, by reaſon of the Plague at <hi>London,</hi> was Adjourned to <hi>Oxford.</hi> The Supplies for carrying on the <hi>Palatine Cauſe</hi> had been preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Lord Keeper before at <hi>weſtminſter;</hi> and now at <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Kings Secretaries of State Report to both Houſes the Kings great Occaſions for Money, and the great Debts left upon him by his Father. Thereupon the <hi>Faction,</hi> having a <hi>Young King</hi> to deal with, and in Neceſſity for Money, began to Rant more than ever with High Debates; reflecting upon his Miniſters as Evil Counſellors, and upon himſelf; upbraiding him, that his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities aroſe from Improvidence; and a world of ſuch like ſtuff they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>witted him with, and cried out alſo on Popery, as if it had been juſt coming in: but in the mean time they neglected the <hi>Palatine Cauſe,</hi> (the ſupplying whereof ought to have been ſpeedy) and afterwards Scandalized the King and his Miniſters, in having the blune of it upon them. Next, they ſell upon High Demands from the King before they would think of a Peny: The ſame <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> as before in King <hi>James</hi>'s days. So the King perceiving they were reſolved againſt Supplies, unleſs they might have their will upon himſelf, and tear his Miniſters and ſome of his Counſellors in pieces, He, after three Moneths ſitting, was forced to Diſſolve them.</p>
                  <p>About five Moneths after that Diſſolution, his Majeſties great Neceſſities urged him to the calling of a <hi>Second Parliament:</hi> which was done, and no ſooner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but the Faction reſumed the very ſame Courſes again; onely in one particular they alter'd: from ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating the Kings Miniſters in general, they now began to fall (in ſtead of Money) upon the Duke of <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>kingham;</hi> though the King in his Speech willed them rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, it was not long ſince in his Fathers time, that <hi>They did ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him, that all the Honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ferred on him w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s too little.</hi> Many hot and high Debates paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; nevertheleſs, in deſpight of the <hi>Faction,</hi> the Loyal part of the Commons made a ſhift to get a Vote for Three Subſidies, and Three Fifteens for the King: but it came to nothing; for though the King after wards wrote a Letter to them, and otherwiſe alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned them to bring him that <hi>Bill of Subſidy</hi> to paſs, telling them he ſhould look upon <hi>Longer delay as a denial;</hi> yet the <hi>Faction</hi> ſo diſturbed the Houſe with <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and Debates,</hi> that nothing was done; the King got not a E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thing, and was conſtrained, after Four Moneths ſitting, to Diſſolve them a <hi>Second time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The next year after, a <hi>Third Parliament</hi> was call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d; and though the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured hard in their wonted way, yet for meer ſhame at length a Subſidy was Voted, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104590:22"/>
paſſed by the Induſtry of the <hi>Loyal Party:</hi> But on the other hand, the Faction ſtomaching the Matter, contrived how to ſhew their Malice another way, and drave on a <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance</hi> to take away <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Poundage,</hi> one of the chiefeſt Maintenances of the Crown: Which to prevent, the King was fain to go Himſelf in Perſon to Prorogue them for Four Moneths time; and that being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igh expired, it was by Proclamation Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued for Three Moneths more; after which being Re-aſſembled, the <hi>Faction</hi> flew out into high Fits about Prieſts and Popery, and Grievances; and were ſo tumultuary, that the <hi>Speaker</hi> was leaving the Chair, but that they held him in by force, till they had paſſed Reſolves <hi>againſt payment of the Kings Tonnage and Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndage:</hi> And ſo what Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney they had given with one hand, they took away with another. So that nothing being likely but Miſchief to the Crown by longer Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> King was glad to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them by Proclamation afterwards, and to acquaint the World with their Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, by putting forth a <hi>Declaration of the Cauſes of their Diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thereupon his Majeſty was neceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itated to have recourſe unto extraordinary ways for Supply, to carry on the Government, without Parliaments, for almoſt Twelve Years after; for by the violent and unreaſonable proceedings of <hi>that deſperate Faction,</hi> which, at every Election, crept in among them, they were reduced into a ſtate, not onely unpracticable and uſeleſs, but <hi>dangerous</hi> to the Crown.</p>
                  <p>During this <hi>Twelve years interval,</hi> the <hi>Faction</hi> now <hi>lay at lurch</hi> in City and Countrey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>retting and corroding in the bowels of the Government; and collecting matter of new accuſations againſt the King and his Miniſters, out of thoſe extraordinary courſes, which the neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty they had forced on them compelled them to take, for upholding the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and which their Factions providence re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erved in mind, on purpoſe to make uſe of, whenſoever time ſhould bring a neceſſity upon the King to call another Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.—It was ſo at length, that they contrived this neceſſity; for they truck'd with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and by correſponding there, brought them into <hi>England</hi> in the Year 1639. which put the King to a great charge to raiſe an Army to oppoſe them: But the matter being compoſed, a <hi>Pacification</hi> was agreed on; the <hi>Scots</hi> were to be paid a ſum of Money, and Money the King muſt provide for them. So neceſſity at laſt made him call <hi>that fatal Parliament,</hi> which began <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1641. Which being met, the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> began now to work on his Majeſty to purpoſe; told him, no Money was to be had but by borrowing, and men would not credit them, unleſs they could be ſure the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament might fit long enough to repay it. So by this means, the King being deſirous to rid away the <hi>Scots</hi> out of the Kingdom, was wrought upon, for raiſing the Money, to paſs that <hi>prodigious Act,</hi> which enabled that Parliament to fit at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> as long as they pleaſed, and ſo to do what they li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Then (you know) how they uſed the King afterward for his kindneſs; what ſtrange things they did, and to what Concluſion at length they came. From whence ariſes this ſharp Inſtruction for all <hi>ſucceeding Kings,</hi> That while this <hi>Faction</hi> reigns upon the face of the Earth, they takeheed of relying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, in a time of the Crown's neceſſity; and of giving them opportunity, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a <hi>new Parliament,</hi> in hope of getting Money; foraſmuch as woful experience hath ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wn us, they, <hi>at ſuch a time,</hi> make it their buſineſs to <hi>ask,</hi> not <hi>to give;</hi> and never to leave aſking, till they come to be diſpoſers both of the King and Kingdom. This is it they would now be at, and have fixed their Party for it all over the Nation, to ſcuffle hard at new Elections. So I ſuppoſe I have ſufficiently cleared my <hi>Second Reaſon,</hi> by ample Experiments; that it cannot be for the King's advantage or ſafety, in ſuch a time as the preſent, to part with this Parliament, and call <hi>a new;</hi> unleſs it were poſſible that <hi>a Leopard ſhould change his ſpots, or a Blackmore his skin;</hi> or that this <hi>Mercurial Faction,</hi> which is now, by its Leaders and Drivers, made more mad than ever for an opportunity,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104590:22"/>
ſhould change its nature, and become tame on a ſudden; and be fix'd in a greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and kindneſs to this King, than they were to his <hi>Grandfather</hi> and <hi>Father;</hi> or, in truth, to the eſtabliſhed Government and Intereſt of the Crown.</p>
                  <q>—Credat Judaeus Apella, Non ego—</q>
                  <p n="3">3. A <hi>Third Reaſon</hi> ariſeth from the natural Temper and Conſtitution of the Party, in reſpect of the Government. He underſtands little that ſeeth not <hi>Presbytery</hi> to be the bottom of all; that Bottom wherein we have ſeen embarquing many years <hi>unpreferred Clergy-men, broken Factions, caſhier'd Courtiers, guilty Officers, by pocritical Citizens, miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Zealots</hi> of both Sexes, old Sinners, but young Saints, and their <hi>pedling Levites;</hi> whoſe work it is, from houſe to houſe, to <hi>blow the Bellows</hi> round the Kingdom: All which uſe to employ their Talents to draw in many of the <hi>honeſt-hearted Gentry,</hi> though not into the ſame opinion with them in <hi>Religious matters,</hi> yet to ſide and vote with them in their <hi>pretences of redreſsing publick Grievances, reformation of Abuſes,</hi> removing, or doing juſtice upon <hi>evil Counſellors;</hi> and the like: And with theſe charms they have been wont to hold many publick-ſpirited Countrey-Gentleman faſt to their ſide, till they have humbled the King, the Court, and all the Faſt-friends of the Government, and brought all to their bow; they give them the ſlip into further proceedings, they pull off their Viſors, ſhew their Faces, and ſlie higher and higher, till they top all that is above, and tumble it down: as they did of old often in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of late in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To that <hi>Malign Ulcer of Presbytery</hi> it is, that moſt of the ill humours of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom flow; becauſe the <hi>Preshyterian</hi> is for ſome <hi>National Government</hi> of the Church, though in ſuch a way as is utterly <hi>inconfident with the Monarchy.</hi> The reaſon of it is plain; becauſe it derives no Power from the King, but pretends only from the King of Kings, <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yet would have <hi>a Secular Influence,</hi> to Govern the Kingdom in their own <hi>Spiritual</hi> way, which is by a <hi>Parity of Presbyters;</hi> a Power purely <hi>Ariſtocratical,</hi> directly contradiſtinct to the form of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> to which the <hi>ſingle Biſhop</hi> only is agreeable, becauſe he arrogates not any influence in Government over the people, but what he derives from the King. Now then, ſo it is, that ſeeing ſome <hi>National Church-Government</hi> is that which muſt be, and the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> is that which is the Kings beſt hold, and moſt firm to him; therefore the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and Leaders of preſent Quarrels, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aln from all their intereſts in Court, common Cunning tells them, they muſt ſtrike in with the men of the other Form, to build new For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes upon the ruine of the <hi>Court,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> if they mean to be great, and Govern; which cannot be more readily done, than by becoming pretended Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the old Government in the Church, and by introducing a <hi>Church-Ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ocracy</hi> into the room of it: for, if one be not, the other muſt be: and if ſo be they ſlip into the head of it, they will never be without ſuch a Conſcience, as will engage them to maintain it, being men of a verſatile principle: So that when I view the Printed Liſts of them, me-thinks I already ſee <hi>Lords States,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Twenty four Conſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ators that would be,</hi> aſſiſted by the <hi>Spiritual Ariſtocracy</hi> of a <hi>General Aſſembly;</hi> for, they reckon all is done, if they can but come to tug for it in another Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                  <p>This brings us to take notice of a <hi>Second Objection,</hi> againſt their deſign of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off the Parliament, which the <hi>projecting Polititia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> ſeem to flight, and 'tis this, <hi>That the Church and this Parliament will fall together.</hi> 'Twere but vain to write
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104590:23"/>
much more, to ſhew the grand probability of it, and of the debaſement, or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, of this glorious Monarchy, if the <hi>Faction</hi> can finiſh what they have proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. But why is it that they utter'd and printed lately ſo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny ſevere Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon his Majeſty and his Government? Why hath this <hi>LETTER,</hi> upon which I have here written theſe <hi>ANIMADVERSIONS,</hi> made it its main ſcope, to caſt all the <hi>Odium</hi> of the evils therein pretended, upon the <hi>Biſhops?</hi> Why have divers Tranſactions been ſolely imputed to them, and they alone been repreſented blame-worthy, if there had been any cauſe of blame in things, which many times had been firſt moved by the <hi>Temporal Lords,</hi> if the deſign were not to exaſperate mens minds principally <hi>againſt Biſhops?</hi> Why are they ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>en ſlandered, as if they drave an Intereſt, <hi>as Biſhops,</hi> prejudicial to the Rights and Intereſt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? What mean all theſe ſuggeſtions, if they meant not to prepare them for ruine by another Parliament, ſeeing they can never do it while this is in being? And why ſo great a zeal againſt them among the <hi>prime drivers of the Faction,</hi> who can own nothing of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or Reformation, ſave what they take up for <hi>cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty</hi> ends, but becauſe they well know there is no way to invade the Throne, but by firſt removing <hi>Biſhops?</hi> which ſeeing this Parliament, their defenders, will never ſuffer; that is the reaſon why ſome have been ſo vehement in debates to imbroil the Houſes, to make it impoſſible for them to do any thing more for the Publick; and ſo by taking away their reputation, they may not be able to defend themſelves againſt the plotted out-cries of the People, to make the <hi>Church and this Parliament fall,</hi> and ſink under the fury of the <hi>Faction</hi> both together?</p>
                  <p>Thus having taken a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urvey of all the other holds of Reaſon, wherein they fortifie themſelves, and infeſt the Government by frequent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>allies forth in print; and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them, and planted better Reaſons in their ſtead, 'tis time to return to the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in Fort which I left; I mean the <hi>LETTER;</hi> which will now be the more eaſily and quickly de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>THe next Seſſion of Parliament, which was <hi>January</hi> 7. following, many excellen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es were in hand in order to a Bill. Among the reſt, one was, That the Princes of the Bloud Royal ſhould all marry Proteſtants.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>TIs rather to be ſuppoſed the Lords are here ſlandered. It can hardly be, that they ſhould take up a buſineſs which was damn'd by King <hi>James</hi> long ago; when the Factions Party in the then Houſe of Commons clamoured againſt the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Match with Spain,</hi> and made Addreſſes to the King about it, who in much wrath told them, <hi>They ſhould meddle with their own buſineſs, this being above them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This point alſo the Faction was ſo bold to inſiſt on, among the reſt of their high De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands made to his Son in the <hi>Nineteen Propoſitions</hi> 1642. to which his Majeſty anſwered, <hi>That to debar him of the free Marriage of his Children, would be to place him in a condition lower than the meaneſt of his Subjects.</hi> This debarring of Princes from marrying where they pleaſe, would be to hinder them from making thoſe great Advantages which many times they might get thereby, for the general Good of the Kingdom. Therefore when it was preſſed on, at the ſecond Reading of the Bill, the Vote went in the <hi>Negative.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:104590:23"/>
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT notes the Duke of</hi> Lauderdale<hi>'s being a</hi> Patron of the Church, and that his Coach was filled with Biſhops; and the Lord Chancellor and Lord Treaſurer <hi>'s</hi> are of a juſt Size to the ſame Affair.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>TWo Faults, it ſeems, theſe two Lords have beſides their being of a <hi>juſt Size to the true Intereſt of the Government;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Two Good Places;</hi> crime enough in this Age for Miniſters of State; for which, while <hi>one man</hi> lives, they are ſure never to he forgiven. I will not ſwear my Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> had a hand in this LETTER; but as weak a man as I am, may be apt to imagine ſo, becauſe he takes ſuch care thoſe two Noble Lords ſhould not be forgotten; nor the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> becauſe he keeps all quiet in <hi>Scotland;</hi> ſo that there is no poſſibility of beginning again the Ruine of our <hi>Engliſh Biſhops</hi> by the way of <hi>Scotland;</hi> nor of getting Friends into a <hi>Scotch</hi> Parliament, to ſecond the fine Speeches made here in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>NOw comes the memorable Seſſion of <hi>April</hi> 13. 1675. than which never any came with more expectation of the Court, or dread and apprehenſion of the People.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>THey were much beholden then to his Lordſhip, to remove their Fears, by taking a courſe to convert the Houſes into <hi>Cock-pits,</hi> to make <hi>ſport</hi> for the Nation. The Court indeed were ſo fooliſh as to expect better things; but this muſt be imputed to the want of his Lordſhips Wiſdom among them. But what was the occaſion that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip laid hold on thus to transform them? His <hi>Pocket-Buſineſs</hi> of <hi>Shirley</hi> did not do all the miſchief: but there was another, called <hi>The Bill of Teſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Bill of Teſt</hi> was brought into the Houſe of Lords by the Earl of <hi>Lindſey</hi> Lord High Chamberlain, a Perſon of great Quality, but in this impoſed upon.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>BUt others are of opinion his Lordſhip did it, as an Act of high Loyalty, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that moſt Noble Character which his Family juſtly bears in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of his Majeſty and the whole World; who can never forget either them, or the memory of that great Man the Father of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Earl of <hi>Lindſey;</hi> who, in the firſt famous Battel of <hi>Edge-Hill,</hi> being Lord General of his Majeſties Army, moſt valiantly ſpilt his Blood in that Service, in hope immediately to have reſtored the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> and to have ſtopt that Iſſue of Blood, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an ſo many years after about the Kingdom. Therefore it was no wonder that this Noble Lord, being his Grandſon, was the Man that brought in a <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ill of T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt;</hi> He and all his being a Family
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104590:24"/>
that can endure a <hi>Teſt,</hi> in this, and all other Concerns of the King, the Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Nation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>IT was then Read the firſt time without much oppoſition. But at the ſecond Reading, the Lord Keeper, <hi>(now Lord Chancellor)</hi> and ſome other Lords, made Elaborate Speeches, the <hi>Keeper</hi> calling it <hi>A moderate Security to the Church and Crown,</hi> and that no Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man could refuſe it; and whoever ſhould, would give great ſuspicion of dangerous and Anti-Monarchical Principles. <hi>And they ſhew'd what dangerous Times we are in, all Men not having laid aſide the Principles of Rebellion.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>CErtainly, it was well obſerved by thoſe Lords: and therefore I ſuppoſe it was high time to take Pen in hand, to manifeſt the Truth, that the late Diſcourſes and practiſes of ſome men, during ſeveral paſt Seſſions of Parliament, are no other but the ſame very courſes that were practiſed with the like heat and violence, and with the ſame method againſt the King, the Church, and the whole State, both in and out of Parliament, as appears through the whole Current of theſe <hi>Animadverſions:</hi> in which I had not been ſo large, but that it was moſt neceſſary to preſent to view, the new Tranſactors of the <hi>Faction,</hi> now dreſt, and acting in the habit, principles and poſture of the old Maſters of the <hi>late Rebellion;</hi> which might lie for ever buried in the <hi>Act of Obli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ion,</hi> if theſe men did not rake all up again into freſh remembrance, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will or no. <hi>God forgive them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Was it not then wiſely and nobly done of my <hi>Lord Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ncellor,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lords, to think of ſome way of Security againſt ſuch Deſigns as we ſee on foot?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>BUt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and ſome other Countrey-Lords, (the good Earl of <hi>Shafts:</hi> a man that in all the variety of Changes of this laſt Age, was never known to be bought, or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighted out of his publick principles)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Riſum teneatis amici?]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He at large open'd the ill Deſigns and Conſequents of the Bill, <hi>and preſſed it might be laid aſide.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>THat Clauſe of his Lordſhips great Conſtancy and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idelity, you have had enough of before, ſo that you ſee his Lordſhips Friend the <hi>Letter-Man,</hi> had a large ſtock of Confidence to pen it; and I am apt to believe Some-body never bluſht at the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it. Nor do I think a common Whore when ſhe brags her ſelf as honeſt as any of her Neighbours, was ever out of countenance. It is at this time a great queſtion among his Friends in the City, Whether they ſhall take Security upon his Lordſhips Honour, that he will be as hot againſt the <hi>Teſt</hi> this time twelve-moneth: For Silk, or Cloth, or St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffs, or the like, they are ready enough to give him Credit; but if ye talk of <hi>State-Commodities,</hi> they <hi>ſhrink the ſhoulder,</hi> and ſay nothing. 'Tis there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely done of him, to talk againſt giving Security for ſuch matters.—But it will next be requiſite to ſee what Form of Security it is, againſt which there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as raiſed ſo loud a Clamour: it is this following, as ſaith the LETTER.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104590:24"/>
                     <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do declare, That it is not lawful, upon any pretence whatſoever, to take up Arms againſt the King: And that I do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe that are Commiſſioned by him in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of ſuch Commiſſion. And I do ſwear, That I will not at any time endeavour an Alteration of the Government either in Church or State.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>LETTER.</head>
               <p>THe Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke with ſuch convincing reaſon, that all the Lords that were at liberty from Court-E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gagements, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lved to oppoſe it to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttermoſt; and the debate laſted five ſeveral days, <hi>before the Bill was committed.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
                  <p>THis certainly is a very ſevere Reflection upon thoſe Noble Lords, who in this day underſtood the true Intereſt of Peerage to be, to <hi>Adhere cloſe and firm to the Crown.</hi> And 'tis known the greateſt part of them had no Engagement to the Court, but what was by <hi>Religion,</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Sence of Honour;</hi> and this is the <hi>Court-Engagement,</hi> not only of all Lords, but of every Loyal Subject. In the other ſort of <hi>Court-Engagements</hi> his Lordſhip was not long ſince ſo much concerned, that when he came to loſe them, no Obligation whatſoever could hold him to <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hitehall</hi> any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>No Peny no Pater Noſter.</hi> The Devil never wonder'd at <hi>Job</hi>'s great Devotion toward the Court of Heaven, as long as God held him in Penſion: nor did I at his Lordſhips, while the King held him in Offices. A multitude followed <hi>Chriſt for the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ves:</hi> but far be it from us, to reckon ſo Noble a Peer as his Lordſhip among the Multitude, though we are told here, that he carried on the <hi>Debate for five days together before it was committed to a Committee of the whole Houſe.</hi> So that by ſuch a behaviour one would think he had never had any <hi>Court-Engagement</hi> whatſoever. For at length, it ſeems, the Debate en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in a <hi>Proteſtation</hi> made by him, and 23 other Lords, againſt that <hi>Oath,</hi> whoſe Names his Lordſhips <hi>Letter-Man</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts down in a <hi>Liſt,</hi> Printed there no doubt on purpoſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage them to ſuch new Reſolutions, for which he may have further occaſion to uſe them. But knowing they are Noble Lords; and to the end that ſpace may be left them for <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Thoughts,</hi> and becauſe of the Honour I bear them and their Families, I forbear to Re-print them. For upon a ſecond Reading, 'tis paſt my Underſtanding how 'tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible any man can, from the Maſter of that <hi>Oath,</hi> have occaſion to make many words of Exception, and Out-cry; or where the harm is, to take an Oath to maintain my Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, if I have right and good Intentions, though perhaps it were not cuſtomary for me, or men of my quality and condition ſo to do, eſpecially in ſuch a time as this, wherein ſo many Mens Hearts and Tongues have been faltering in thoſe Reſpects, and the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which they owe towards the King and His Government. Nor can I conceive, there being no other intent in thoſe Noble Lords who were for the taking of the Oath, but to give the Crown a <hi>Security</hi> in a dangerous time, how it can be cenſured <hi>An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement of the Freedom and Priviledges of Peerage;</hi> when as it is clear, that if the Crown be unſecure, the danger is more to the Peers than to any other part of the People? For when the Popular Storm ſhall fall, if Monarchy fail, then farewel to Liberties, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104590:25"/>
Peerage and all. Nor let any part of the Lords ſlatter themſelves that they ſhall fare better than others; or that if a Rebellion ſhould begin again (which God forbid) it would be poſſible for them to hold any ſhare in Authority, more than thoſe Lords did who Sate and Acted againſt His Majeſty after he was driven away by Tumults from <hi>weſtminſter;</hi> they may remember themſelves alſo were at length not only driven away by Tumults, but by Tumultuary Proceedings, the whole Order of <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf were ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> extirpated. <hi>what hath been</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) may be, and there is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r the Sun.</hi> A ſharp Precedent it is, ſufficient to inſtruct you and your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity to judge, that no Security can be given too much to the Crown in a tottering time, when Popular Clouds and Heats do gather and melt in the Sky, and when there is (as I have made appear) a viſible Storm read<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to fall, firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> on the Court and the Biſhops, if ſome men may have their wills; then you know what enſues to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all the reſt of the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>What a ſhame then would it be to me, to trifle away time much longer, by inſiſting upon that unſavoury <hi>LETTER,</hi> which ſo induſtriouſly takes care to ſet f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rth the Good Parts, and other Qualities of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> that one would think it had been written on purpoſe?</p>
                  <p>What need we trouble our ſelves, how his Lordſhip and his Partners Signed the next day a <hi>Second Proteſtation,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n a <hi>Third</hi> the day after that? I could never tell before what Religion my Lord was of: Sure, he is now a very notable <hi>Prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tant.</hi> What need we tell that he got the other Lords, his Friends, to ſet their Names to the laſt as well as the two former <hi>Proteſtations?</hi> His Lordſhip took care to dip them in the <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>-pot;</hi> he will have no <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>; over ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s too;</hi> then they are <hi>ſeaſon'd,</hi> and can be no <hi>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To what purpoſe ſhould I repeat what this <hi>LETTER</hi> tells, how ſome Lords ſpun out ſuch <hi>DIVI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ITY</hi> about <hi>State-Oathes,</hi> that one would even ſwear they had been furniſh't by their own new Chaplains? or how one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord argued, <hi>That no State <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity by Oathes?</hi> I think ſo too among <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e ſorts of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ians:</hi> but I remember, among the <hi>Heathens</hi> an Oath did ſignifie Somewhat; and that of old it was thought Wiſdom, and good Policy by all the World, By Oathes to oblige men unto Obedience and Loyal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y. We are aſſured, the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ther of the Faithful, Abraham,</hi> did ſo in his Kingdom, he being reckoned in thoſe days a mighty Prince<hi>:</hi> And it was to oblige his ſervant to ſecure the Succeſſion of his Principality, by ſuch an Alliance as himſelf had appointed, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 24. 3. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Verſes. <hi>I will</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſwear unto me by the Lord, the God of Heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n, and the God of the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. It follows, <hi>And h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Serva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t put his hand under the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of</hi> Abraham, <hi>and ſware to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> concerning that matter.</hi> In another place alſo we find King <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> making <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to Swear, not to deal falſly with him and his Poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erity. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>Abraham ſaid, I will Swear. Abraham</hi> was then within the Kingdom of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and had protection from him, therefore took an Oath of Fidel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y to him. Both which Oathes had certainly never paſſed had not <hi>Abraham</hi> thought it lawful for him, both to exact, and to give an Oath of Fealty. Which is no more than what is contained in that <hi>Oath of the Teſt;</hi> about which the <hi>Proteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> made ſo great a Buſtle, that the Debates (as this <hi>LETTER</hi> ſaith) took up <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> debate together.</hi> And in the foregoing part of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> you may remember I noted, that in the printed Arguments of their Lordſhips, it was confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Conſcience about an Oath ſoever was pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nded) <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> part of the publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and that ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>upon might follow a fair occaſion to make an Out-cry, to be rid of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104590:25"/>
That <hi>Oath of Teſt</hi> differs but little from the <hi>Oath of Allegiance;</hi> and 'tis ſhrewdly to be ſuſpected, that he who contends againſt this, would refuſe likewiſe the other Oath, if it were tender'd u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> him again. Nor can I ſee why he ſhould ſcruple the one more than the other, unl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> it be for the ſake of this one good Clauſe in it, that he was by the <hi>Teſt</hi> to have ſworn, <hi>That he ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ors that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by the Kings Authority againſt his Perſon:</hi> a Doctrinal diſtinction uſed (as I told you) in the beginning of the late Wars; a meer device to pull ſcruples out of mens Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they might fool them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elves into an opinion, that they fought for the King, as well as the Parliament, though they ſhot their Bullets againſt his Preſence and Perſon: ſo that in caſe they had ſhot him dead, they were ſtill to underſtand it was no hurt to his Authority. Thus the Pope heretofore, and his party, when by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence they Excommunicated Kings, and Depoſed them as <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and imployed Villains to aſſaſſmate them, ſteel'd their Conſciences, for the doing of the fatal deed, with a like diſtinction, <hi>That they killed the Heretick, not the King.</hi> Which comes all to one end with our new <hi>Jeſuitical Poſition,</hi> That you may in your minds ſeparate a Kings Authority from a Kings Perſon; then uſe it to take Arms againſt him; which if he reſiſts, you are to conceive he reſiſts the <hi>Kingly Authority;</hi> by conſequence becomes an Enemy or Rebel: and ſo if in the reſiſtance you kill him, <hi>you kill the Rebel, not the King.</hi> But this is not the only point of ſubtilty wherein our fine <hi>Spinners of Theology and Policy</hi> do agree with the <hi>Jeſuites.</hi> Was it not then (think ye) high time for thoſe Noble Lords to promote that <hi>Oath of Teſt,</hi> and inſert in it that moſt neceſſary Clauſe of <hi>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orring</hi> ſo damnable a Doctrine? For, whoſoever he be that refuſes to declare his abhorrency of it, and perſwades men publickly to the like refuſal, doth as good as give an open alarm to the State, and threaten Rebellion; while he prepares and draws a party into the ſame perſwaſion, and opens unto them ſo ready a way to it. So that from a ſort of people ſo inſtructed, I eaſily grant, there can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>no ſecurity by Oaths, unto any State whatſoever;</hi> as ſome of the Proteſters did affirm.</p>
                  <p>But the LETTER proceeds further about Oaths, and tells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <hi>Chriſt himſelf hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h Oaths;</hi> and that <hi>Groti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Jure Belli &amp; Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is,</hi> ſeems to make it plain from <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 34, 37. <hi>Swear not at all, &amp;c.</hi> Lord! what Abſurdities will not men ſay and do, when they are out of humour! I ſhew'd before how ſhrewdly their <hi>Proteſting</hi> Lordſhips were put to it in point of State, to borrow Arguments from the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llers;</hi> but now for Divinity about Oaths, they are fain to borrow of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and would fain make <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> a <hi>Quaker</hi> too: but yet they con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs he doth but <hi>ſeem to make plain</hi> the Doctrine; therefore, ſince 'tis no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worth the while, nor have I time, to ſhew them at large their miſtakes of the Authors meaning, I affirm what is plainly the ſence of thoſe Texts.—The <hi>Jews</hi> had among them an ill cuſtom of mingling Oaths with their <hi>ordinary Communi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tion,</hi> ſuch as theſe; <hi>By Heaven; By the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arth; By Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> and <hi>By my Head.</hi> Theſe are nothing of kin to <hi>State-Oaths,</hi> or Oaths before a Magiſtrate; but the prohibition intended there by <hi>Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> is againſt idle and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ane Oaths in common Converſation; as appears by theſe cloſing words, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication be Yea, yea; Nay, nay: For, whatſoever is mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>il.</hi> Our <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>viou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> reſtringeth manifeſtly the ſence and ſcope of his words to mens evil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and the ſtreſs of his prohibition is laid upon common Oaths in diſcourſe, (as is obvious to any man well in his ſences) and it cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e wreſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d againſt Oaths of any other kind, without the torture of an <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> And yet it muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>-Oaths</hi> when his little Lordſhip will have it ſo, and hath a mind to lead about, and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> or doze a company of his <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Believers.</hi> But it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> boldly ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104590:26"/>
to preach ſuch ſtuff upon thoſe Texts as he did, in the very <hi>Temple of wiſdom,</hi> I mean, that Sacred Aſſembly of the Houſe of Peers, where his Majeſty is ſuppoſed to be always preſent.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs, we are told by the <hi>Letter,</hi> that in the ſame Houſe they had every day, from his Lordſhip and his friends, one <hi>Sermon</hi> or other as good as that; not upon Points of Divinity, but upon <hi>Niceties,</hi> and <hi>Quillets,</hi> and <hi>Quibbles,</hi> and <hi>fine-ſpun Cobwebs</hi> of Policy; telling the World how to <hi>bound Monarchy,</hi> and ſhackle Kings <hi>with fear of Humane Reſiſtance;</hi> and not leave them <hi>onely to the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> of God to reſtrain them.</hi> Thus the <hi>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Kings is meaſured by his Lordſhips little B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>el;</hi> He <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſes as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s;</hi> implies the <hi>Fear of God</hi> to be of little force to govern Kings and Stateſmen; and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that <hi>Never any Countrey, free like ours, ſuffered any Standing Guards to be about their Prince.</hi> The <hi>Guards</hi> (it ſeems) are great Blocks in the way of the <hi>Faction,</hi> that the deſign cannot march on ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt as they would have it. His Lordſhip hath the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>olves</hi> in <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Fables, and would give us ſuch Advice, as if he took us all to be but <hi>Sheep,</hi> ſilly enough, to conſent, that the King ſhould part with His <hi>Keepers;</hi> and then the <hi>Faction</hi> knows how to <hi>HANDLE HIM without Mittens.</hi> It was the fear of <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>New Sedition,</hi> that firſt ſet up theſe <hi>Guards;</hi> and then both Parliament and People rejoyced in them, as moſt needful for the ſafety of their Prince and his Government. But now, when <hi>FACTION</hi> is at the <hi>HEIGHT,</hi> and BRAVES the KING to HIS FACE in HIS <hi>HIGHEST COURT,</hi> in a <hi>MORE AUDACIOUS MAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NER</hi> than at firſt <hi>THEY</hi> did HIS FATHER, it is HIS LORDSHIPS <hi>OPINION</hi> the <hi>Guards</hi> ſhould be taken off: and then, What ſhall hinder the <hi>Sheep</hi> from being brought to <hi>Slaughter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>LETTER</hi> tells alſo, what other ſtrange Inſtances were Preached in the ſame Houſe, and ſelected out of the times of ſome weak <hi>Princes,</hi> to ſhew, that ſometimes it can be <hi>no Traiterous Poſition,</hi> to affirm, That Subjects may take Arms againſt perſons Commiſſioned by the King, though the King be among them in Perſon. What is this, but to argue from particular Caſes of extraordinary Contingency, to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch men from Duties of ordinary Practice; contrary to all <hi>Logick</hi> and Rule of <hi>Argumentation?</hi> and from thence alſo to conclude, 'tis an Invaſion of the Subjects Liberty, to impoſe upon them an Oath, to Swear for the Security and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the King in a time of Publick danger, and the viſible Approches of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion?</p>
                  <p>It tells us alſo, how the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> went on next, to find fault w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th that Clauſe of the <hi>Oath of Teſt,</hi> which obliges not to make any <hi>Alteration in the Church, or State.</hi> It ſeems, not onely his Lordſhip, but ſome others alſo were touched to the Quick by it; and, it was a ſign of ſome Conſcience in men, to ſtartle at an Oath to be taken againſt <hi>Alteration,</hi> when nothing but <hi>Alteration</hi> is intended, with an irreparable diminution of the Government both in Church and State; as hath been manifeſted throughout this Diſcourſe already.—Firſt, for the <hi>Church,</hi> Who can judge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when as the <hi>LETTER</hi> gives next an Account, how the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> in a Speech treated the Church? ſome think he did it ſpightfully, and that he was too Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mically bold in reflecting upon the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> the <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> and the <hi>Canons.</hi> All which were (as the <hi>LETTER</hi> ſaith) handled at large by his Lordſhip; and, To what end was it, if not to make way for an Alteration in the Church, and all her Concerns, from the preſent Eſtabliſhment? His Lordſhip well
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104590:26"/>
knows 'tis a little too dangerous for any man, to Open his MOUTH yet a while a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King and the State: That was not ventur'd on at firſt, by the BOLD FEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOWS of 41. That comes of Courſe, after the Faction hath been ſluſht with baiting of Biſhops. The Alteration of them is deſigned not too fierce at firſt; but, they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, as their Old TUTORS did formerly, by ſteps. They of old did declare at firſt, That THEY had <hi>No intent to let looſe the Golden Reins of Diſcipline in the Church;</hi> yet, in a turn or two of the year, they were ſo extravagant as to deſtroy it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce another; and then <hi>Hell brake looſe</hi> aginſt the State as well as the Church. There is ſo ſtrict a Connexion and Dependence betwixt them, that if you part with the one, the other lies open to the next Aſſault, and you ſhall part with it alſo. Or if the leaſt diminution befall the <hi>Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>opal Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ipline and Government,</hi> ſo as but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qualifie the <hi>Biſhops Dignity,</hi> with an intermixture of <hi>Presbyters ſubordinate,</hi> which (I hear) is the firſt part of the Deſign; ſo much of an allay will, by neceſſary conſequence, be given to the Crown, Kingly Power and Intereſt. For, a Single Perſon Governing a Dioceſs, is, 1. More anſwerable in its Form to a Monarch: and he knows nothing, that knows not what a mighty Influence <hi>meer Form</hi> hath upon the very Minds of men, and the Affairs of the World. 2. The greater the Power and Dignity of the Biſhop is, the more able he will be, upon all Occaſions, to Aſſiſt the Crown. 3. He muſt alſo be the more ready; becauſe, when <hi>ſingle,</hi> he will not be impeded by a <hi>Clog</hi> of Advices and Importunities of the <hi>croſs-grain'd</hi> Brethren; who, by the Charm of well-acted Sanctimony, which ever gains upon the Ignorant Vulgar, will always be ſtealing away the Hearts of the People from him; and conſequently from the King; becauſe they will ever reckon themſelves more obliged to follow <hi>Popular Patrons,</hi> who will always be concerned to favour them more than the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as Inſtruments more likely to ſerve <hi>Popular Ends.</hi> For theſe Reaſons, it will be the Crowns perpetual Intereſt, to maintain the Epiſcopal Power entire and unmixt. Give the <hi>Presbyter</hi> but an <hi>Inch,</hi> and he will ſoon take an <hi>Ell.</hi> The natural <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>Faction</hi> is, in Activity beyond the <hi>Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ites,</hi> reſtleſs and proud as <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and in hypocriſie as compleat and zealous as a <hi>Phariſee.</hi> Who ever reads the <hi>Histories</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> where they have had any thing to do, will find this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter is true. And for Fidelity to Kings, I remember King <hi>James</hi> in his <hi>Baſilicon Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: Believe me,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who have tried them; that you ſhall find more Faith among Highland Thieves and Robbers, then in this Faction.</hi> 'Tis a true <hi>Serpent;</hi> for if he can but get in his Head among the Biſhops, he will ſoon <hi>wind in his whole Body</hi> into the beſt ſhare of Eccleſiaſtical Authority; and as much as the Biſhops loſe is loſt from the King, whenever the Presbyters and their <hi>Patrons</hi> ſhall pleaſe to joyn Reſolutions to diſpute him. There is one in the World underſtands this ſo well, that he thinks it worth his while to ſpend whole Days and half Nights in Parliamentary Diſputation againſt this Oath; that ſo a Door may be kept open for ſome Alteration. And if ever it comes, (which God forbid) it may be gheſſed what the Crown is like to get, whenas the 29. Page of the LETTER ſaith, <hi>[The Lords againſt the Bill of Teſt were in no ways ſatisfied, but plainly ſpoke out, That Men had been, might, and were likely to be, in either Houſe, too much for the King, as they call'd it.]</hi> Which certainly was an odd ſaying to come out of the mouth of a Lord: therefore I ſpare his Name.</p>
                  <p>But the LETTER is ſo crafty as to take another courſe; for to make ſure of their Lordſhips to the <hi>Faction,</hi> it tells what this, and that, and t'other Lord ſaid, and how Wiſely, and Learnedly, and Gallantly, and Wittily every Lord of that Humour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted himſelf, and ſets down every one of their Names to the Account<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Though it
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104590:27"/>
be a queſtionable Point, whether a Twelve-moneth hence any one Lord will think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obliged for the Courteſie.</p>
                  <p>So I have done with that LETTER, and leave the World to judge, what he deſerves who wrote it; and what he who prepared the Materials, and then ſupplied the <hi>Pen-Man</hi> with them. As for the Publication of them, it did put ſo high a Provocation upon both Houſes of Parliament, that they concurred in an Order, which condemned it (as it) to be burnt by the <hi>Hangman.</hi> And it was accordingly executed. The Reviving o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it now at this time, we judged moſt neceſſary, to the end that a <hi>ſecond Execution</hi> might be done upon it publickly, by force of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as well as by <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
